<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sinners safetie, if heere hee looke for assurance by Richard Barnerd ...</title>
            <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1963.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20188764</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20188764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09319)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1703:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sinners safetie, if heere hee looke for assurance by Richard Barnerd ...</title>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.L. for T.M. and Ionas Man, and are to be sold at his shoppe at the West doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Richard Bernard.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-G⁸ H².</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Man (Christian theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23753:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23753:1"/>
            <p>THE SINNERS SAFETIE, If heere hee looke for <hi>aſſurance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Barnerd,</hi> Preacher of Gods word, at <hi>Worſop</hi> in Nottingham-ſhire.</p>
            <bibl>Coloſſ. 3. 1.</bibl>
            <q>If yee then be riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe thinges which are aboue, where Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God.</q>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by H. L. for T. M. and Ionas Man, and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe at the Weſt doore of Paules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:23753:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23753:2"/>
            <head>To the Chiefe Officers, the Gentlemen domeſticall Attendants, and to the reſt of the Familie of the moſt Reuerend Father, <hi>Tobias,</hi> the Lord Archbiſhop of Yorke his Grace, the chiefeſt good is hartily wiſhed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, I vviſh you vvell, I hope you doubt not; in my loue to you all I offer this my labor: to ſome, as deſired, in lieu of good vvill and kindneſſe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. My beſt thoughts are tovvardes you in the beſt things. Naturall fauorits, vvorldly friends, wiſh good to the body: that doe I; but vvithall, the ſoules ſafety: vvithout vvhich, no good.</p>
            <p>You do heare the excellent truths of God, by one of whom it hath been ſaid, <hi>He doth regnare in pulpitis.</hi> I doe graunt it, vvho can deny thoſe gifts? yet let your loue pardon my folly; and reiect not my well meaning, though I ſet before you a candle at noone. The matter is not amiſſe, if the rudeneſſe of ſpeech make it not diſtastefull: if ſo, it were a fault.
<pb facs="tcp:23753:3"/> Loue doth not loath vvhat is good: wholſome meat meanely cookt, is acceptable to a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry ſtomacke. What hath been heard vvith the eare, may nowe bee ſeene with the eye: a double remembrance; the other leſſe, this of more continuance. I hope the fruit vvill bee anſwerable.</p>
            <p>The text is a ſpeciall iewell, ſet forth with precious pearles. The argument is of weight, <hi>How a poore ſinner may haue aſſurance of the greateſt happineſſe.</hi> The exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſheweth our ſlowneſs, but the neceſsity of the thing requireth our diligence: good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therefore. What matter ſo vvoorthy our trauel? to gaine all vvithout this, is but loſs. We liue here in pleaſure and eaſe: is this our comfort? are vve at home then? is there not to come a <hi>weal</hi> vnſpeakeable, or a <hi>woe</hi> into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, vvith ſorrovve to liue in paine, both in time, and euer beyond all time? Sinners vve be: hence conclude vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e muſt death, and that double. By this apprehenſion, is nothing but horror of <hi>Hell.</hi> Aſſurance of happineſſe, concludes ſafety, and ioy of <hi>Heauen:</hi> One of deſert; but this not vvithin compaſſe of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: it is Gods gift in mercy, comfortable, a ioy vnſpeakeable.</p>
            <p>Wee all ſhall ſee the Lord in the laſt day (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb facs="tcp:23753:3"/> Atheiſticall Athenians mocke at the doctrine of the Reſurrection): but we al ſhal not alike behold him, as vvee doe not alike deſire his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. Some ſhall ſee him a lamb, and apprehend fierce vvrath, and ſay; Oh mountains couer vs. Some the lyon of Iudah, and conceiue ioy; and in comfort, cry aloude, <hi>Hoſannah.</hi> Good cauſe vvhy: they haue peace by aſſurance of pardon and it is the day of their redemption; that did they ſeeke for diligently; this they expected, &amp; deſired ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly, and in the end enioy the revvard.</p>
            <p>To ſtirre you vp heerevnto, is the drift of my preſent endeuour. VVe all need ſpurring; heauie harts, and leaden heeles, loaden we are with iniquitie: ſo ſlovve to goodnes, that all our daies vvee hardly get any grace perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, accept I pray you my kindneſs: read vvith a mind ayming at the end which I propoſe. Serious meditation helps memory, and ſettles iudgement; but in practiſe ſtands the life, vvhich getteth alſo commendations. You are in eminent place: tongues on both ſides talke at liberty; our defence is innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. No way can ye ſo glorifie God, as by prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; nor advaunce, before the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, the honour of the moſt Reuerend your
<pb facs="tcp:23753:4"/> Lord and Maiſter more, then by a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: ſo doe, and it ſhall bee alſo your glory. If heerein my labor further any thing, it ſhall be my ioy: and if we continue in vvell dooing, it it doubtleſſe wee ſhall obtaine mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Which the Lord grant, euen ſo. Amen. From my Studie at <hi>Worſop.</hi> Nouemb. 12.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing Friend euer in the Lord, Richard Bernard.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:23753:4"/>
            <head>The Sinners ſafetie, if <hi>here he ſeeke for aſſurance.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. PET. 1. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Wherefore, Brethren, giue rather diligence to make your calling and election ſure: for if ye doe theſe things, ye ſhall neuer fall.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <note place="margin">The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles drift, with the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence.</note> is, that with Profeſſion, men ſhould ioyne San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the 5. verſe he exhorteth thoſe, to whom hee writ, that they ſhould giue all diligence to fly the corruption which is in the world through luſt; &amp; this is the maine propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:23753:5"/> or leſſon intended. And to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therunto, he firſt teacheth them the meanes how to attain to a holy conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, by adding vertue to vertue, one grace to another, as hee ſheweth in the <note place="margin">An inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> 5. 6. and 7. verſes. A duetie of a miniſter who is a ſpirituall Phyſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſoule, not only to ſhew the malady, or aduiſe his Patient to haue care to his health; but alſo to preſcribe the meanes how diſeaſes may bee remoued, and health preſerued. <hi>Salomon</hi> commendeth the feare of God. <hi>Pro. 1. 7. The feare of God is the beginning of Wiſdome:</hi> and in <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. preſcribes the meanes to come to the vnderſtanding thereof, in the 1. 2. 3. and 4. verſes: <hi>My ſonne, if thou wilt receiue my words, and hide my commandements within thee, &amp;c.</hi> In the fifth verſe hee concludeth, and ſaith, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſhalt thou vnderſtand the feare of the Lord, and find the knowledge of God.</hi> In like manner <hi>Peter,</hi> (in <hi>Act:</hi> 2) after he had accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Iewes for putting Chriſt to death, reſteth not in manifeſting their miſerie; but readily teacheth them how they may acquite themſelues, and eſcape the deſerued, iudgement
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:23753:5"/> for ſuch a ſinne.</p>
            <p>To ſhew miſerie, without remedy; is to lodge the heart in ſorrowe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reliefe: meanes muſt be ſhewed with the matter; the way with the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iourney: the minde poſſeſſed with the one, teſteth not content without the other. Therefore muſt miniſters af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Apoſtles example obſerue this order; as both reaſon and neceſſity it ſelfe requireth.</p>
            <p>After the Apoſtle hath preſcribed the meanes, hee vrgeth reaſons to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the practiſe of the doctrine, by vſe of the meanes: the reaſons are, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee ſhould not be idle and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruit in our profeſſion, verſe 8. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe elſe we are blinde, and cannot ſee afarre of, and alſo forgetfull of a great and incomparable benefite, that wee are purged from our old ſinnes, verſe 9. becauſe otherwiſe wee cannot haue aſſurance of our ſaluation; which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is in my text, verſe, 10.</p>
            <p>In which againe to vs miniſters is <note place="margin">An other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to miniſters.</note> commended with the Apoſtles wiſedom (to be able to ſhew meanes to attaine to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23753:6"/> that he would haue them doe) his godly care alſo, to haue them to vſe and not to neglect the meanes which hee hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vnto them. Therefore doth hee preſſe them with ſo many reaſons, and vrge them with ſuch arguments, leaſt they ſhould bee wanting in this duety. For indeed men are loath to lay good things to heart; and more loath to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe.</p>
            <p>Wee are like <hi>Balaam;</hi> heauen can we wiſh, <hi>O that we might die the death of the righteous:</hi> but wee would not liue their life. Fleſh ſeeketh after eaſe, &amp; the way to life is ſtrait: we would not be as <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> here, but like <hi>Diues</hi> fare deliciouſly euery day, and yet like <hi>Lazarus</hi> looke for heauen at our ending. Therefore it is needfull for miniſters to vrge and to ſet vs on forward, &amp; to follow our ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh nature with reaſon vpon reaſon, as ſo many goades pricking our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to cauſe vs to ſtirre our feete, and ſo go on in the way of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Bare narrations to ſlowe diſpoſitions are of no force. And, if words take place without waight of reaſon, it is either the worke of faith, which is rare; or le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23753:6"/> of affection, which is too common; and to which agreeth well the prouerb, <hi>Soone ripe, ſoone rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> A Iewiſh intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt, to day <hi>Hoſannah,</hi> to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>Crucifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs then ſay, &amp; ſhew why: that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding may be informed, &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſetled with reaſon.</p>
            <p>Suſpect the ground ſandy, where the houſe is built with ſound of words: a little ſtorme will ſhake it, and eaſily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow it.</p>
            <p>Such as are won ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly (as a diſeaſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber perfectly healed) will abide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. And thus much for the Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p>The words diuide themſelues into <note place="margin">The diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Text.</note> two generall parts:</p>
            <list>
               <label>1. An exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in note,</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The ground of it, in the word; <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 The parties exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>Brethren.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 The matter of the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the words following;</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Giue diligence to make your calling and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <label>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:23753:7"/>2 A reaſon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is contained a promiſe: wherein note,</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 The condition thereof: <hi>If yee doe theſe things.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 The thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, in theſe words; <hi>Ye ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Of theſe, as the words lie in order. But firſt it is not to bee omitted, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle vſing, in this verſe, a reaſon to enforce the embracing of vertue, as is aforeſaid, doth not barely ſet it downe, as the former, but deliuereth it by way of exhortation: which argueth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles affection in ſpeaking; deſiring that this reaſon might not onely bee vnderſtoode, but alſo embraced with affection. For exhortations are to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the affection to make men zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, as doctrine is to make them iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; both neceſſarie to feede the ſoule. Vnderſtanding without feruencie of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is cold entertainment: ſuch growe ſooner full of policie, then pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, the beſt is luke-warmenes; a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that God cannot beare, but muſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23753:7"/> needes ſpue them out of his mouth: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> for either the <hi>Lord</hi> or <hi>Baal.</hi> And if affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be alone, it is but folly, running into ſchiſme or ſuperſtition. Therefore muſt men be vrged to affect that which is taught.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> But in that the Apoſtle is ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in this reaſon, that they may get aſſurance of ſaluation, he commendeth vnto vs, the waight of this argument, chiefly of all other to bee affected: And indeede, if wee conſider that without aſſurance wee are altogether comfortleſſe, who would not hereby be moued to embrace vertue, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe himſelfe therein?</p>
            <p>Without aſſurance, though we haue poſſeſſion of the beſt good, wee are not in perfect ioy. Vncertainty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nuance of happineſſe in a happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, maketh the ſame leſſe comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the minde often charged with feare of too ſodaine an end. No man hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, but hee ſeeketh to know a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine terme: and hee that hath a Leaſe for many yeares, would alſo make it his owne by purchaſe for better aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:23753:8"/>
            <p>Aſſurance is a ſalue to cure feare, it is a ſtay in wauering and diſtruſt, &amp; the beſt ſafety againſt deſperation, that dreadfull ſoules miſerie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Therefore let it moue vs to be vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that ſo wee may get aſſurance.</p>
            <p>For aſſurance of Land, wee will be at coſt to pay money: for certaine gaine, wee do trauell farre: to bee ſure of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, wee will ſerue long, euen hard Maſters, in drudgery; great men, &amp; not without ſlauerie. And is a vertuous life, a ſeruice to the Almightie, the father of mercy, nothing worth? is it ſo loathſom or irkſome that we cannot indure it, to haue aſſurance of heauen, the gaine of Glory, and the honour of Angels with Chriſt for euer?</p>
            <p>Oh! hearken and conſider the one and the other. What is the aſſurance of all the world without hope of heauen? The bodies bliſſe; caryon: the ſoules death; damnation. Now to the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore:</hi> that is, becauſe, vnles you <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Paraphraſe, explaining the word, for to raiſe the doctrine</note> haue theſe vertues, you ſhall be but idle profeſſors, fruitleſſe, blinde, vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God, and without any aſſurance of ſaluation: therefore giue diligence to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23753:8"/> liue vertuouſly, and to make your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; election ſure. It is a word, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how that which followeth, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on that which goeth before: from which we learne, That the diſcommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <note place="margin">The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> of the want of theſe vertues, and the good inſuing by them, ſhould make vs ſeeke to be endued with them.</p>
            <p>To auoid danger bodily, and to get <note place="margin">Reaſons to inforce it.</note> aduantage to our ſelues in earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, wee are moued to ſeeke after thoſe things, by which wee may eſcape loſſe, and gaine ſome good.</p>
            <p>Men ſtudie to become learned, men labour for friends, they trauel for riches, and ſeeke for promotion, onely for that the benefite of them is ſo much for mans welfare; and the want thereof held ſo greatly hurtfull, as without them, men are but iudged miſerable: and yet lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and friends, riches and honour, are nothing at all either ſo auaileable to make him happy that hath them, as hee that hath grace; or ſo miſerable, that wanteth them, as hee which is without grace.</p>
            <p>Holy vertues are a pledge of Gods loue, the fruits of the ſpirit, the hand wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he benefit of vertues &amp; heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graces &amp; what they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re.</note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:23753:9"/> of God in our hearts, witneſſing his loue, and confirming his couenant with vs. They be ſo many ſtaies from ſlyding in ſlippery proſperity; ſo many potions, purging out vices; ſo many pull-backs from vanity; and ſo many comforts in aduerſitie. They be marks of Gods children, and pleaſant flowers to decke vp ſweetely our Temples the dwelling of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>What compariſon betweene hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning, and heauenly vertues? betweene riches of the world, and this wealth of the ſoule? betweene theſe friends here, and Gods good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour? between earthly greatnes, &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall grace? none at all. And is there any equality in the loſſe? nothing leſſe. A man that hath grace and vertue, may be and is happy, though he want lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, riches, honour and friends: But enioy all theſe without grace; ſee the ende. <hi>Hamans</hi> honour occaſioned his hanging: <hi>Abſoloms</hi> beautie was his bane: the young mans wealth held him from Chriſt: <hi>Achitophels</hi> learning and wiſedome was his deſtruction; and all this came to paſſe through want
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23753:9"/> of grace and theſe heauenly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. To conclude, when men are wicked, yea in a high degree of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe, we ſhewe the cauſe in one word, when wee ſay they are grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore, if the feare of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <note place="margin">The vſe with exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> diſcommoditie, or deſire of the benefit of the greateſt good in anie thing may moue vs to ſeeke for it, to auoide the one, and poſſeſſe the other; let then the goodnes of vertues moue vs to ſeeke after them, to attaine vnto them: let vs embrace them, and euermore liue in the holy practiſe of them: for, nothing worſe then to want them; and nothing more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable then to haue them. It follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brethren;</hi> The parties exhorted: all thoſe hee meaneth as had attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Fratres v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terini.</hi>
               </note> to faith in Chriſt, and did make profeſſion of the Lord Ieſus, verſe the firſt, whome here hee calleth by <note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> the name of brethren; as vſuallie the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paule</hi> alſo doth in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, who tearmeth thoſe to whom he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23753:10"/> writ (euen the Gentiles) brethren; not by nature, not by nation, nor by kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, but by profeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> The Prophets before Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming (a thing to be noted) though they ſpake vnto their owne nation, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of one ſtock; yet in their prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Note well.</note> they did call vpon the people by the name of <hi>Iſrael: Children of Iſraell, Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the land,</hi> and ſo forth: but neuer by the name of brethren, as <hi>Peter</hi> begun in the <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 19. and the Apoſtles elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: to ſhew a difference of the lawe and the Goſpell euen in the meſſengers: the one ſort, meſſengers of the lawe, were ſeuere, and ſpake further off from affection of loue: the other, publiſhers of glad tydings, were louing meſſengers of peace, &amp; ſpake as to children of their father, and brethren in Chriſt, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth here. In which hee ſheweth firſt his loue to them whome hee wrote vnto: In which grace, miniſters muſt <note place="margin">Inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> teach, if euer they will do good.</p>
            <p>Rancor and malice are not fit for preachers of peace: neither cholerick paſſions, in proclaiming ioy by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpell: loue abandoneth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23753:10"/> the one, &amp; bridleth the other; yet ſo as there remaineth a godly zeale to rebuke ſinne, as we ſee the Apoſtles did.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Secondly, he declareth his great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, equalizing the ſaints all of them, the meaneſt as the greateſt, with himſelf; an other vertue for miniſters: a vertue <note place="margin">A pattern for mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> of incomparable eſtimation: It is the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle where God will cock vp his graces; a cheſt for his ſecrets, his owne lodging place, there delighteth he to dwell. It is <note place="margin">Humility commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Eſa. 57. 15 Mat. 11. 29</note> the grace which hath the promiſe of grace; and one of the vertues by which Chriſt himſelf commended himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his diſciples, &amp; therein to bee follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them. It procureth loue, it allureth mens hearts to haue a good liking of ſuch, yea and winneth reuerence: for he that humbleth himſelfe ſhall bee exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>This is not ſpoken to take away or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Preuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> in ſuperiority; but onely to beate downe pride, that men may walk in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. Neither may hence the inferiour preſume to chalenge equalitie, becauſe the ſuperiour deſcendeth lower then his place. It is humility in the better, when he maketh himſelfe meaner then hee is:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23753:11"/> but it is arrogancie in the other to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance themſelues thereby beyond that they are. If men in authority finde any ſo preſumptuous; let them claime their due, to ſuppreſſe that pride: which they may doe with commendation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Againe, hence may bee noted, that men by profeſſion of Chriſt become co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 18.</note> in a fraternity and brotherhood. They haue God to their father, who hath begotten them by his word; the Church is their mother that bare them, for ſhe is called his wife: they haue all one elder brother the Lord Ieſus, &amp; al in him taught by Chriſt to call God, father.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> Therefore let vs acknowledge this brotherhoode, not onely by calling ſo <note place="margin">Vſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> one another, as the cuſtome was in the primitiue Church, but by liuing as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the dueties of loue. Let vs not be called <hi>Rabbi,</hi> for wee are brethren: <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 8</note> Let there be no diſſenſion amongſt vs, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, for we are brethren: Be <note place="margin">Gen. 13. 8.</note> at peace one with another: O how ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <note place="margin">Pſal. 133. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> a thing is it for brethren to dwell together in vnity!</p>
            <p>But ah alafle! hath our profeſsion brought vs to any ſuch practiſe? where
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23753:11"/> is any thing leſſe then loue? ſeeke for v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and behold enmitie. Loue is not <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man for himſelfe,</hi> as we now vſe: but it is carefull for other, whom wee little regard.</p>
            <p>The life of loue is brotherly kindnes: but what ſhall I ſay more? we haue loſt this goodnes: kind to none, no not to our owne kindred; carefull for none, but for our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Selfe loue hath withered vp all bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly compaſsion, that we cannot ſhew forth any workes of mercy with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration. But where loue is wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, there God is loſt, for God is loue: where this brotherhoode is neglected, there the commandement of loue is not regarded; and where this is out of vſe, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing rightly performed.</p>
            <p>Therefore let vs better bethinke our ſelues hereof, remembring our profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to minde this duetie: beleeue wee cannot our vnion with Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out communion of his Church: and pray wee cannot to GOD, but with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of brotherhood, ſaying, <hi>Our father.</hi> If then wee haue either truth in profeſsing, ſoundnes in beleeuing,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23753:12"/> or a right minde in praying, wee muſt walke in loue towards our brethren for preſeruation of this holy fellowſhip, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en vnto the end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giue rather diligence.</hi> This word <hi>rather</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Luk. 11. 28</note> is not here a note of choiſe, as if men might chooſe whether they would bee diligent or no: but it is a preferring of one thing before another; and is alſo a ſecret correction of the ill diſpoſition of na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure, which hath a <hi>rather,</hi> that is a will and deſire to the things of this life, then to ſeeke diligently after heauenly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, the good things of the life to come. And it is, as if hee had ſaid; Though by <note place="margin">A Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe.</note> nature you be apt to bee diligent for the things here, for bodies welfare; yet I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you for ſoules ſafetie, to giue rather diligence to get heauenly graces. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> In which hee teacheth, that men naturally make an ill choiſe preferring things of the world which haue an end, before things ſpiritual which haue no end. And this we ſuck from the breaſts of our firſt parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> who beleeued Satan before God, in hope of earthly good; &amp; aduentured the Lords diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the loſſe of Paradiſe for the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23753:12"/> gaine of an apple. <hi>Eſau</hi> would deſpiſe his birth right, for a meaſe of pottage: the <hi>Gadar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> would want Chriſt, rather then their ſwine: <hi>Iſraelites</hi> deſire the fleſh pots in Egypt, before the heauenly Manna: <hi>Demas</hi> biddeth adue to the Goſpell, and embraceth the preſent world: And the Rulers loue the praiſe of men more then the praiſe of God.</p>
            <p>Thus hold wee byaſſe in this courſe, as we haue a naturall inclination: but to heauenly things wee may finde altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in vs an indiſpoſition: yet ought we rather to giue diligence vnto that which may better our eſtate hereafter for euer, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, who reſpected <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> not the world; and therefore obeyed he the voice of the Lord, and went hither and thither as a ſtranger and a pilgrime whither God thought good. And aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, till we can preferre heauen before earth, grace before goods, happines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore honour, we neither will nor can be zealous in profeſsion, nor vpright in practiſe.</p>
            <p>This Rather giuing diligence to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, and nothing elſe, made <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> walke with God, <hi>Noah</hi> to liue righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23753:13"/> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> to refuſe his honour, to fly the pleaſures of ſinne, and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer rather affliction with the people of God.</p>
            <p>This preferring of ſoule before the <note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> bodie, and eternitie before mortalitie, made <hi>Daniel</hi> reſolute without daunt of ſpirit to ſerue his God; and the three children not to bee fearefull to anſwere the king boldly, euen when his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was changed for anger againſt them. And therefore let vs here take <note place="margin">The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation and vſe.</note> the Apoſtles counſell, and follow after a true and perfect good, rather then that which is falſe and but deceiuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>The more wee loue that which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue vs, the leſſe ſhall we like that which is belowe. Encreaſe in the ſpirit, killeth the fleſh: and a deſire to bee with Chriſt, worketh a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of the world. Chuſe rather the better, and it will withdraw eaſily affection from the worſe. Affect to be with the faithfull, and thou wilt ſoone hate the ſociety of the wicked. Light wil not indure darkeneſſe, truth falſhoode, vertue vice: Chriſt will not ſuffer communion with <hi>Beliall:</hi> where
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23753:13"/> the Arke commeth, <hi>Dagon</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alleth downe.</p>
            <p>We ſee then to conclude, If we be ill; why we are no better, the cauſe is, for that we care not to bee diligent for the beſt things: the vertue whereof is ſuch, as it euer forceth men to amend that which is amiſſe, more or leſſe, at one time or another. And of this, thus much.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diligence.</hi> The Apoſtle vſeth a <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Expoſition. Paraphraſe.</note> word of great emphaſis; Study, do your endeuour, and ſeriouſly: as if hee had ſaid, bend your wits to bring this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter about, ſet your mindes vpon it, bee muſing of it, and do your endeauour, go about it as much as lyeth in you, and that in good earneſt, attending thereto; conſidering it not as a light thing, but as a matter of great weight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he would teach vs; that euery kinde and manner of going about the matters of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is not inough: but God requireth therin our earneſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor. He commandeth vs to loue him, but alſo <hi>vvith all our Heart, with all our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Minde, with all our Soule, and with all our Strength.</hi> Dauid ſaith: <hi>O my ſoule,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 103. 1.</note> 
               <hi>praiſe the Lord:</hi> and hee addeth, <hi>and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23753:14"/> all that is within me praiſe his holy name.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 9</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> commandeth to keep our ſoule, but addeth <hi>with diligence.</hi> This Apoſtle willeth vs to fly the corruptions which are in the world, verſe 4. and he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to doe it <hi>with all diligen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> verſe 5. ſo as our beſt endeuour is required. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> And therefore let vs be diligent herein; let vs ſeriouſly be emploid in the holy exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of religion. <hi>All that thine hand ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 10</note> 
               <hi>find to do, doe it with all thy power:</hi> and the reaſon is giuen, <hi>becauſe there is neither worke, nor inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, nor knowledge, nor wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the graue whither thou goeſt. Bee not lither,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>in thy buſines,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 11</note> 
               <hi>but feruent in the ſpirit ſeruing the Lord. Curſed,</hi> ſaith the Prophet Ieremie, <hi>is hee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 48. 10.</note> 
               <hi>that doth the worke of the Lord negligently.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee then that we are bound, vpon a great penalty, to bee diligent in the Lords buſines. Wee ſhould ſo loue the houſe of God, that the zeale thereof (with <hi>Dauid</hi>) ſhould eat vs vp. It ſhould, (as Chriſt ſaid of himſelfe) be foode vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, to doe the will of our father. We muſt not only deſire, but hunger after righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>We are not onely to take occaſions
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23753:14"/> to ſerue God, when they are offered, but ſeeke till we find the meanes. <hi>Seeke the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> 
               <hi>kingdome of God,</hi> ſaith our ſauiour: <hi>labour for the foode that endureth to eternall life.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6. 27</note> 
               <hi>Seeke thoſe things,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>which are aboue:</hi> ſo as wee are to take great <note place="margin">Col. 3. 1</note> paines to go to God, and ardently affect good things without weary ſomeneſſe, Therefore <hi>Salomon,</hi> in exhorting men to get the feare and knowledge of God, <note place="margin">Prou. 2.</note> doth vſe words of great force, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of likeneſſe in things wherein men do vſe the greateſt endeauour to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Pro.</hi> 2. 2. 3. 4. he ſaith not Heare, <hi>But cauſe thine eare to hearken;</hi> not haue a liking, <hi>but incline thine heart,</hi> force it with violence &amp; might; not pray for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edge, but <hi>call</hi> for it; not ſpeake, but <hi>cry for vnderſtanding:</hi> not get wiſedome, if thou maiſt careleſly ſtumble vpon it, but <hi>ſeeke her as fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er and ſearch for her as trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: then ſhalt thou vnderſtand the feare of the Lord, and come to the knowledge of the moſt higheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, hence iuſtly are reproued <note place="margin">Vſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe to diuerſe worldlings.</note> diuerſe ſorts of ill diſpoſed perſons. Firſt thoſe that are vp earely and do go to bed late, eating the bread of carefulnes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23753:15"/> for the world: to it, they are violent in affection; for it they neglect no time, they omit no ſeaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they muſe vpon it; they, like moles, make their habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the earth, and can ſauour nothing but it; day and night theſe wormes doe worſhip this their God Mammon, and in their trauell they haue all their wits about them (as we ſay) to manage their buſineſſe: But for their future beeing in bliſſe hereafter, they haue no care, they thinke all time miſſpent that way; of religious dueties they make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience at all: If they ſpeake of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, it is but by the way, no point of ſet purpoſe; If they pray, it is but in words, their hearts are farre from it, faſt a ſleepe in their bed-ridden prayers, before they haue halfe made an end; wander they doe in their thoughts, no ſtabilitie of minde towards GOD. They are ripe of tongue in worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: and for witte therein, can none go beyonde them; but in matters of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, they bee as Idols, or as the people <hi>that haue eies and ſee not, eares</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 14. 15.</note> 
               <hi>and heare not, and hearts but perceiue not:</hi> But why is all this? <hi>Leaſt they ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23753:15"/> ſee with their eies, and heare with their eares, and ſhould vnderstand with their hearts, and ſhould returne, that God might heale them.</hi> So then, if wee be ſuch, it plainly appeareth, that wee runne the way of death, and walke in the path of perdition, except we do amend.</p>
            <p>Let ſuch worldlings conſider that the world they muſt leaue, going as they came, naked, with nothing; and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiue, not as they were in wealth here, a place there: but as they were religious, ſo ſhall they be rewarded. And therfore ſith this world vaniſheth, and cannot help, but euen as wee haue ſought the Lord, ſo ſhall wee find comfort; let vs be more diligent in ſeeking after that, which will maks vs euer happy without alteration euerlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>Againe, the voluptuous liuer is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <note place="margin">Voluptuous liuers.</note> leſſe, then of this minde to ſeeke diligently thoſe things that are aboue: but hee, as a beaſt, maketh his bellie his God; and the ſatisfying of his luſt, his chiefeſt life. Nothing ſauours with him but pleaſures: therefore ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth hee his daies in curſed delights, and ſaith as the careleſſe Rich man,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:23753:16"/> 
               <hi>Soule liue at eaſe, eat, drinke, and take thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke. 12. 19</note> 
               <hi>paſtime:</hi> when in his ſtrength, and in the midſt of his pleaſures hee thinketh of death, he thereby ſtirs vp his minde the more to his euils, ſaying as an Epicure and Atheiſt, <hi>Let vs eate and drinke, for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>to morrowe vve ſhall die:</hi> hee maketh a league with death, and a couenant with the graue: if all die, he dreameth to liue; though God threaten damnation, yet he will preſume of mercie, vntill the verie daies of euill come, wherein he will be forced to ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them. When ſicknes hath ſommoned him, and feare of preſent death hath taken poſseſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, then happely wil he ſay: Oh I haue ſinned, pray for me; I haue ſpent my daies leudly, what ſhall I doe? and if in this agony, conſcience ſeaze vpon him, then he will roare for feare of hell, then houle and cry out in dread of damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, oh ſaue; but none ſhall ſuccour: oh heare, but God will not hearken; woe is <note place="margin">Pro. 1. 28.</note> me for my wantonneſſe, wo is me that I haue wrought ſuch wickedneſſe: good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes I regarded not, I therefore now feele no comforts of grace: oh that GOD would let me liue againe, how would I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23753:16"/> then ſeek after him? fie vpon filthy luſt, curſed pleaſures a due, vanitie of vanities and vexation of ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Beloued, if we but felt what men feele for ſinne in trouble of conſcience and without comfort, we would not for the world be in their place: wee eſcaping the danger would ſoone leaue ſinne, &amp; giue all diligence to doe good, in which onely reſteth all our comfort; then with gladnes and alacrity of ſpirit wee would ſet forward to the worke of the Lord, embrace goodnes and liue vertuouſly, that wee might not come into the like miſerie any more.</p>
            <p>Therefore let the feare of it aforeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d moue vs to giue all diligence to do wel, that we may neuer taſte of that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full torment, the apprehenſion of Gods wrathfull diſpleaſure, for which Chriſt ſinneles, for our ſinnes ſuſtaining, fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch an agony, as in the garden hee ſwet drops of bloud (wretched man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou this) and on the croſſe cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>My God, my God, vvhy haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27. 46</note> 
               <hi>me?</hi> and ſhall we ſinne rebelliouſly, and preſume of mercie? ſhall hee (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, as it were) feare, who was without
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:23753:17"/> ſinne, and that day and night ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter good things? and may we be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in voluptuouſneſſe, and (careleſſe of religion) bee wholly without dread? O vaine imagination, Sathanicall deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, curſed preſumption! Let vs bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe minded I beſeech you, &amp; think better of it.</p>
            <p>There are alſo an other ſort (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude) <note place="margin">Careleſſe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, cold Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</note> who though, as theſe forenamed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they bee not wretchedly addicted to their wils, running headlong into wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and wholy careleſs of religion to the very end: yet are they idle i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their profeſſion, and not carefull to vſe their time ſo well as they might, but will be content to let occaſions, offered, ſlip; and do thinke that men may be too cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, too preciſe, making more adoe then needeth, that they can ſerue God and heare not the word twiſe on the Sabbaoth: once a forthnight, or once a moneth may content them: that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes may withdraw from theſe too ſometime; ſo as a little liketh them well, yea and leſſe then nothing now &amp; then ſhall not diſpleaſe them. But theſe worke not out their ſaluation with feare
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23753:17"/> and trembling: theſe doe forget how the fiue fooliſh virgins let their lamps go out for want of watchfulneſſe, and did knock too late when the gates were <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 11 12.</note> ſhut.</p>
            <p>The ſpouſe in the Canticles, loſing the <note place="margin">Cant. 5. 3. 6. 7.</note> preſent opportunity, in her ſluggiſh &amp; careleſſe diſpoſition, had almoſt loſt Chriſt: who yet after ſought him, and found him; but not without ſtrokes and wounds giuen by the watchmen.</p>
            <p>It will bee iuſt with God to puniſh our careleſneſſe: we haue the word offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we may enioy it: bee not loathing of this Mannah, be diligent in ſearching the ſoules ſafety. It may come to paſſe, that when we would, we ſhall not haue it: and whilſt we ſeeke and happily find, we ſhall haue no ſmall trouble before wee enioy againe our peace.</p>
            <p>We ſhould followe religion and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious exerciſes (in the compaſſe of our calling) as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did <hi>Eliah;</hi> neither tarrie at Gilgall, nor at Bethel, nor at Iericho, <note place="margin">2 Kings. 2.</note> though wee be entreated: that is, by no means, nor by any occaſion to leaue off, for feare of loſing the bleſſing, if wee be but a while abſent.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:23753:18"/>
            <p>Let vs, as <hi>Ruth</hi> proteſted to <hi>Naomi,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 1. 16 17.</note> ſo ſay for religion, wee wil not be intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to leaue it, nor depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, whither it goeth wee will go; the Lord do ſo to vs, and more alſo, if ought but death de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part it and vs. It is <hi>Eliah</hi> to double bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon thee: It is <hi>Naomi</hi> faire and beautifull to the ſoule, though ſometime <hi>Marah</hi> to the fleſh. Hence is it, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 1. 2.</note> ſaith, Bleſſed is he that meditateth in the lawe of God both day and night. He was not of the minde of theſe vaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours, nor of their practiſe: who, not content with the day, would riſe vp at midnight to praiſe the Lord. The ſpirit of God in godly men hath taught them to thinke, that they ſhould giue all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to be religious, &amp; that they ſhould not content themſelues with formal and cuſtomarie ſeruice, nor at their leiſure now or then from worldly buſineſſe or carnall delights, to thinke of heauen; but daily were they in exerciſe of religion, what eſtate &amp; calling ſo euer they were in. <hi>Dauid</hi> a King did not neglect it: <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> a Captaine was a deuout man, and <note place="margin">Act. 10. 2. 30</note> prayed God continually: <hi>Hannah</hi> was in the Temple day and night: <hi>Peter</hi> was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:23753:18"/> in his holy meditation and prayers at noone: and <hi>Daniel</hi> a great States-man, <note place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> became ſo curiouſly preciſe in his holy deuotion and ſeruice vnto God, that he would not, (in the perill of his life, plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all the Nobles of Perſia by an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuocable decree) ceaſe off to pray, as he was wont to doe, three times a day: and yet was he not (as men religiouſly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted now are tearmed) a good plain ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple man, one of Gods fooles, of a good meaning, but of no great witte; for by <hi>Ezechiel</hi> the Prophet, hee was called the wiſe <hi>Daniell.</hi> Indeede he imployed not wholly his wiſedome after the world, as men now doe: hee ſuffered religion to haue in him the rule; which men in theſe daies haue leaſt regard of: Hee would not be politick to loſe the peace of a good conſcience, which carnall men for honour and wealth care not to make ſhipwrack of.</p>
            <p>If theſe examples be of no force to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men to thinke that wee can neuer be religious enough, nor ouer-preciſe, ſo wee keepe within the compaſſe of the word for a warrant; let them conſider the Lord Ieſus, who was without ſinne,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:23753:19"/> vncapable of euill, &amp; prone to all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet did hee addict himſelfe to holy exerciſes, praying whole nights thorow; then aſſuredly ought we to doe much more then wee doe, yea more then we can ſhould we doe, and as much as we can is too little: for when we haue done all that; yet ſtill are we vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</p>
            <p>For the world, we thinke wee doe <note place="margin">We keepe no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in earthly things.</note> neuer enough: to ſatisfie our wils, or our ſelues in wilfull pleaſures, wee iudge it not amiſſe to keepe no meaſure: delight draweth vs to ſpend much time, to bee at much coſt; yet nothing too much, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too deare: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtfull appetites ſet vs to labour, both long and tedious; yet to attaine the purpoſe propoſed, we can endure the paines: in a word, nothing after our corruption is at any time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that which is meete: where Will ruleth and the heart delighteth, there nothing for that is vntunable, nothing vnmeaſurable, though in ſuperſtition &amp; ſetting vp of Idols. Iſraelites will giue their earerings, &amp; appoint a day for coſt and expenſes, becauſe they will haue a golden calfe. Papiſts practiſe herein
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:23753:19"/> doth ſhewe this plaine: they go farre on pilgrimage; they burthen themſelues with infinit number of prayers; they are at great coſt to maintaine many Prieſts and many orders of their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they night and day ty themſelues to their taske; thrice a weeke they faſt; many daies in a yeare they keepe (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their faſhion) holie, and doe ſtriue to doe more then euer God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that they might merit. And ſhall the pure religion of Chriſt, the truth of God be held ſo little worth, as wee wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly ſhould imagine that wee therein can doe too much? that we may therein be too holy? Surely theſe enemies of God, this antichriſtian generation, ſhall riſe vp in iudgement againſt vs, except religion be of more precious accompt, we better in practiſe, and ceaſe to be ſo too too prophane, as too many be; whom the Lord God of heauen amend in his due time, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:23753:20"/>
               <head>To make your calling &amp; election ſure.</head>
               <p>THere are diuerſe ends of our vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Firmam vel certam, rata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veſtram vocatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; electio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem faccre.</hi> Eight ends of good workes.</note> liuing in religion; To ſhew our loue and thankfulneſſe to God in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; to winne ſuch as are not yet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; to confirme the conuerted; to ſtop the mouthes of the wicked, ſhaming them by wel doing when they ſpeake ill of vs; to make our calling and election ſure, as the Apoſtle here exhorteth; to aſſure to our ſelues that inward graces in vs are true, and not counterfait; to ſhew that we are truly ingrafted into Chriſt; and laſtly, for the mutuall benefit one of another, for our quiet peaceableneſs in the Church and Common-wealth. Theſe ends of good workes wee finde in the word: theſe we acknowledge &amp; know to be attained by well liuing; but that popiſh point of good workes wee may not approue, to doe good workes to merit heauen by in any ſort, a deuiſe of man without the word. It taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <note place="margin">Many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by works.</note> from the ſufficiency of Chriſts ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: it lifteth vp the heart of man in the imagination of his owne worthines:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:23753:20"/> it is contrary to Chriſts words, <hi>When you haue done all you can, you are vnprofitable ſeruants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The godly are commended for good workes, but not ſaid thereby to merit; rewarded they are, but it is onely in mercy: our beſt deedes are imperfect; &amp; ſo farre as wee rely vpon workes of the lawe, ſo farre are we accurſed, and haue loſt righteouſnes by faith in Chriſt: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God we ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d iuſt in Chriſts iuſtice, the forme of our iuſtification is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Chriſts righteouſnes, or the mutuall donation and acception (the giuing and receiuing) of Chriſt Ieſus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God in his mercie and a poore ſinner by faith. Our goodnes is a men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous cloth, and none wholly ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in perfection. In <hi>Adam</hi> we loſt our ſpirituall life: In Chriſt and by him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and alone, wee purchaſe our primarie happines, but not perfectly till wee be in heauen in our owne perſons. Accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly blinde, therefore, as beetles are our Antichriſtian aduerſaries, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo many ends of good workes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed plainely by the Word, yet cannot ſee them, but haue added one of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:23753:21"/> their owne, againſt all truth, againſt the honour of Chriſt, yea and a mans owne ſaluation.</p>
               <p>And thus much to preuent the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie in his hereſie of merit by workes: of which wee had occaſion to ſpeake both from the Apoſtles ſcope, vrging to a vertuous life by the argument here laid downe, the gaining of aſſurance of ſaluation thereby; as alſo from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe reading of this text; for in ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> it is thus: <hi>To make ſure by good works your calling and election,</hi> and ſo it is in the vulgar which is commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly called <hi>Ieromes</hi> tranſlation: which may well ſtand with the drift of the text and truth of diuinity in this point; as that very reaſon added to this exhortation ſufficiently confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. Let the aduerſarie peruert good things as he pleaſeth, veritie is warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: Words of good workes ſound well euer to religious mindes, though peruerſe ſpirits wreſt them heretically to an ill end. But to proceede;</p>
               <p>Two generall leſſons may be colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from this matter of the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, that it is no eaſie thing to be in our ſelues ſure of our ſaluation, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:23753:21"/> in the way of life; becauſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle vrgeth vs to ſo great diligence, care, and endeauour about it: which if it were eaſie needed not. Light things aske not much labour; eaſie things are ſoone done, and wiſedome requireth not to be much about a little: therefore in that, whereunto the ſpirit preſſeth with ſuch reaſon, &amp; vrgeth with ſo earneſt an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, as here; there is difficultie, &amp; to attaine thereunto it is not eaſie? And for proofe of this doctrine, let vs weigh I beſeech you, how hard a thing it is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">How this doctrine is confirmed.</note> into the way; to abide in it being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; how eaſie to decline from the right way; &amp; what trouble is in the recouery, if euer we returne back at all.</p>
               <p>Before we come to God, ſure wee are <note place="margin">Iohn. 8. Ephe. 2. 1. 2. 3. 2. Tim. 2. 26</note> the diuels; no child ſo like his father, as we be like Satan our gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fire, who doth rule vs, &amp; that as he pleaſeth: ſtrong hold he hath of vs: eaſily he wil not let vs go. In our ſauiours time, he tormented, rent &amp; tore the bodies of men, whom he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, before he would let go his hold; ſo loth is he to loſe vs, not of loue, but to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoure vs. If thus he ſtriue to keep poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the body, how hard it is to win
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:23753:22"/> out of his hands bodie and ſoule? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to if wee adde our owne madnes herein, that we vnwillingly are deliuered, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſiſting the meanes, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the meſſengers ſent to recouver vs that would bring vs into the ſtate of grace, then any way willingly yielding our ſelues for our bettering; wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but graunt it true, that it is hard for vs to enter into the way of ſaluation.</p>
               <p>We are naturally like wilde beaſts, <note place="margin">Hard to win men to God.</note> loth to be tamed; we can better away to be ſauages, to liue in our corruptions af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our luſts, then walke in any orderly courſe, if vnpleaſing to the fleſh. What adoe is there to winne men from their wickednes? ſome of vs from our whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſome from drunkenneſſe, ſome from blaſphemous oathes, ſome from greedy couetouſnes, ſome from ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, ſome from one thing, ſome from an other, but eſpecially from our belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued perſonall ſinne? God may thunder from heauen againſt rebellious Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, but they will not amend: Chriſt may lay lode vpon the conſcience of <hi>Iudas,</hi> and tell him, that it were better he had neuer beene borne, then to bee a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:23753:22"/> traytor to the ſonne of man; but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtay him, couetouſnes ſo hath taken hold vpon him: <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> may call the Phariſes a generation of vipers, yet will they ſtill eate out their Mothers ſide, and keepe their conditions: And he may perhaps by long and much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour bring <hi>Herod</hi> to doe this and that, but <hi>Herodias</hi> will he not forſake: So loue we to liue in ſinne, leaſt Sathan ſhould wholy loſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>nd God fully enioy vs. Wee neede n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>her confirmation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but the witnes of our owne hearts. Many Sermons haue we heard, ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one manner, ſome after an other, to bring vs into the right way: our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences haue accuſed vs often, &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs to feare wrath and deſtruction: good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of other before vs; Gods mercies motiues ouer vs; his chaſtice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vpon vs; &amp; the rule of reaſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs to reduce vs; yet haue we not left off to doe wickedly: as if wee had ſworn with a high hand to reſiſt both God and all good men, to bring vpon our ſelues deſerued damnation: forlorne caitifs &amp; accurſed wights may wee thinke our ſelues, and hence condiſcend to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:23753:23"/> truth, that it is very hard to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be good.</p>
               <p>As it is not eaſie to enter into the <note place="margin">Men hardly abide in the way; when they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</note> ſtraite gate: ſo is it a thing of no leſſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie to abide, hauing ſet foote into that path of peace. For we beeing in the ſtate of grace, though wee haue true graces, yet are we not therein perfect; and the imperfection of good argueth ſo much of corruption; this affecteth corrupt things, and pulleth vs from the deſire of that which is holy. Hence is it, that a man findeth in him a continuall combat, ſometime the fleſh preuailing, ſometime the ſpirit: with faith is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: with will is an vnwillingnes, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to euill; but to doe good is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with vs: whereupon it commeth to paſſe, that we ſinne often, and euery ſin interrupteth the comforts of a peaceable conſcience; which maketh vs call into queſtion the aſſurance of ſaluation, and worketh much ſorrowe of heart: ſo that euery man may with the Apoſtle cry out ſaying, <hi>O miſerable man that I am,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſhall deliuer me from the bodie of this death?</hi> Vpon this our imperfect ſtate &amp; corruption, Satan doth take aduantage,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:23753:23"/> hee layeth baites to allure vs, and ſnares to entrap vs, according to our perſonall infirmities, from our natural diſpoſition; he maketh motions by internall ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, or elſe prepareth externall obiects for the ſenſes to drawe away the heart: by both or either are wee deceiued; hee tempting, and wee ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yielding, or but weakely reſiſting. Thus brought he out of the way per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Adam,</hi> iuſt <hi>Lot,</hi> faithfull <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> meeke <hi>Moſes,</hi> holie <hi>Aaron,</hi> zealous <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſtrong <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and that wiſe <hi>Salomon.</hi> What man was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer encountred and not ouercome, if GOD did not aide the beſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with his ſecond grace? We then ſee it to bee as hard, to abide, as to make entrance into the way of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Eaſily wee ſlippe out of the way, <note place="margin">Hard to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer after relapſe.</note> hardly go wee on, back can wee run faſt: but when wee are gone from home, wee make ſmall haſte to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe: long lay <hi>Dauid</hi> in his ſinne, ere hee recouered, till the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> came and awoke him in theſe plaine tearmes ſaying,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:23753:24"/> 
                  <hi>thou art the man.</hi> Sathan giueth ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 7</note> if a childe of God bee taken wandring, as he can ſcarcely finde the way home againe: He either bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs ſo with pleaſures, that we cannot returne, or affrigheth vs with feare, as <hi>Adam,</hi> that we dare not. If we get out of his hands againe, and by Gods good mercie outrunne him, yet is it with ſuch ſtriuing, as wee almoſt faint betweene feare to be held, and hope to eſcape: weighing Gods iuſtice with our ſinne, we dread damnation; conſidering our back ſlyding, ſcarcely dare we looke for mercy, but with ſighs, grones, &amp; teares, wee come lamenting to the throne of grace, confeſſing ſometime with the prodigall ſonne, <hi>Father I haue ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> 
                  <hi>heauen and againſt thee, I am not worthy to be called thy ſonne, make mee as one of thy hyred ſeruants:</hi> ſometime con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing <note place="margin">Luke 18.</note> with the Publicane and crying, <hi>Lord haue mercie vpon me a ſinner,</hi> ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging with <hi>Eſra</hi> our vnworthineſſe, ſaying, <hi>O my God I am confounded, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſdra. 9. 6. 7</note> 
                  <hi>to lift vp mine eies vnto thee, ô my God:</hi> and praying with Dauid, <hi>Haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 6. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>mercie vpon me (O Lord) for I am weake:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:23753:24"/> O Lord heale me for my bones are vexed: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, O Lord, deliuer my ſoule, ſaue me for thy mercies ſake.</hi> And thus it may be, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many teares, lowd cries bitter wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and long ſute made, we find at the length fauour and pardon: Hee that commeth the eaſilieſt, returneth with confeſſion of vanity of vanities; all is but vanitie in his mouth, and with vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of ſpirit in the heart: but many cry, and weepe. powring downe many a ſalt teare from the eie for their former folly, before they obtaine mercie. Much trouble then and difficulty is in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of a ſinner.</p>
               <p>To conclude, many men of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <note place="margin">Many of ſingular note haue fallen, and neuer could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. 2. Kings. 9 10.</note> gifts, of great note in the Church, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for worthy acts, haue falne, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer returned againe: as appeareth in couragious and valiant <hi>Iehu,</hi> a captaine for the Lord of hoſtes againſt the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who ſlew two kings, <hi>Iehoram</hi> and <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> of Iuda and Iſraell: by him was <hi>Iezabel</hi> caſt downe that curſed Queene, and the dogs did eat her in the gates of Iſreel; hee ouerthrew <hi>Baall,</hi> his Prieſts and temple, he was zealous for the Lord and tooke <hi>Ionadab</hi> to bee a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:23753:25"/> witneſſe thereof with him. So <hi>Demas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 4. 14.</note> intertained the Goſpell, accompanied the Apoſtle in his afflictions, ſaluted the Saincts, and was famous in Churches. <hi>Ioaſh</hi> long liued religiouſly; he honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">2. Kin. 12.</note> godly <hi>Iehotada,</hi> and was counſelled by him, he repaired the Temple, and did many things worthy praiſe. <hi>Iudas</hi> was a follower of Chriſt three yeares, he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Chriſt; in his name caſt out diuels, <note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> and was an Apoſtle, one of the twelue, choſen by Chriſt out of all the world; yet was not <hi>Iehu</hi> his heart vpright, but he embraced <hi>Ieroboams</hi> calues, and fell from God and claue to his Idolatrie: yet did <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mas</hi> forſake the Goſpell and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained this preſent world, and no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his returne againe: yet did <hi>Ioaſh</hi> fall to Idolatrie and cruelty, ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods worſhip, and perſecuting yea murthering his prophets without repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: And laſtly <hi>Iudas</hi> became a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miſcreant, a thiefe, a traytor, and in horrour of mind ſo deſperat, as after the fact, being hopeleſſe of mercy he hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf: Who readeth &amp; feareth not? who heareth and trembles not? we ſee our beginning; is it eaſie thence to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:23753:25"/> our ending. Doe wee ſee ſuch, ſo qualified, ſo famous men to fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vtterly? &amp; ſhal we preſume of a better end with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuch tokens of grace?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> By all this which hath beene ſaid, it <note place="margin">The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are deceiued that think aſſurance of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on eaſily atteined.</note> is more then manifeſt that it is not eaſie to attaine aſſurance of ſaluation. It is therefore altogether a fault in ſuch, as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor the leaſt in this matter. Of the world we feare to want: heauen wee make no queſtion of. For the body here wee take care, and doe vpon euery light occaſion diſtruſt &amp; fall to ſhifts in feare of want: but for the ſoule wee make our ſelues ſure that it is well, albeit it doth want all the meanes of ſaluation, and we our ſelues liue in our naturall corruption vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed. What is this but carnall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption? it commeth from Sathans ſuggeſtion; A motion from the diuine ſpirit it is not, where this giueth hope of heauen, there it moueth to goodneſſe; this teacheth that the aſſurance of things aboue after death is beyond reaſon, and therefore more hard to bee attained, then things belowe in this life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Many waies are here to make ſupply for the bodie in earthly things;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:23753:26"/> but one way for heauenly. Men may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon thee for this time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but God onely for the time to come: Thine own labour here may procure thee mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and what thou canſt not get, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may giue thee: but no man can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme a ſoule and giue life, man muſt let that alone for euer: here wee are led by ſenſe, but in the other by faith: money can here purchaſe, but onely mercy there: man may deſerue well of man, but nothing can he merit of God: We may be ſuperiours amongſt men, and yet tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the future good of the ſoule may be worſe then beaſts: <hi>Diues</hi> may fare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly euery day, and yet bee ſo farre from aſſurance of life, as that he is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at his death: All the world may we winne, yet loſe our owne ſoules: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> can tell vs, that hee neuer ſawe the righteous forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> touching the things of this life, but the wicked flouriſhing, &amp; yet come to a fearefull end. The way is brode, and the gate wide, that leadeth to deſtruction, and many runne that way; but the gate to heauen is ſtraight, and the paſſage narrow, leading to life, and many ſeeke it, but fewe finde it: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:23753:26"/> ſet foote in the way, few go on any time; and of theſe fewe, ſome turne back againe, and a very ſmall number perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere to the end. Of the world wee are, and the world will loue her owne: but we are vncapable of grace, and enemies to goodnes, ſo as God in iuſtice abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs. In the world we may liue, thogh we haue offended in many things, (kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them ſecret from men) and neuer make ſatisfaction, but in an other wee cannot, if but one ſinne be vnrepented of and God not ſatisfied, and the price of blood payed to redeeme vs by faith in Chriſt. Here offences committed, may bee pardoned by many (the King not taking notice of them) but there is no euill in the ſoule (though neuer ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret) but the King of heauen is acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſame, and a pardon muſt be procured from his owne perſon, and by none but by his own ſonne: elſe that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor ſhall vtterly be condemned, and pay the puniſhment duely for euer, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the treſpaſſe. Therefore if all theſe things be well conſidered, and the weight of the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſeriouſly weighed, we may rather ſuppoſe our ſelues to be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:23753:27"/> deluded by imagination, to thinke the aſſurance of ſaluation to be ſo eaſily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, then to be the ſettlednes of our iudgement from a grounded perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And thus much for the firſt leſſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> The ſecond leſſon is this; that yet there is in this life a true aſſurance of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, in a certaine meaſure, to euery one in time ordained to be ſaued: elſe the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> here would not haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted vs to labour for this aſſurance; which the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule</hi> attayned alſo <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 38</note> vnto in this life: which hee publiſheth not onely ſingularly in the behalfe of himſelfe, but plurally for the reſt of all thoſe whom God loueth in Chriſt Ieſus. Neither doe I ſay that it is that <hi>fulneſſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>of faith,</hi> but a certaine meaſure; nor at once, but by little and little; nor to euery profeſſour, but to ſuch as are ordained to eternall life. And this is effected by <note place="margin">How to get aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. By medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> meditation, inſpiration, &amp; ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>To haue aſſurance, we muſt meditate of Gods inchangeablenes, both in his owne nature (<hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 17.) as alſo in his gifts and calling which are without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance (<hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 29) we muſt think v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Gods euerlaſting decree without
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:23753:27"/> alteration: of his promiſes made irreuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably with the manner of deliuery, in the time preſent (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 36) <hi>He that beleeueth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 36. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>in the ſonne hath euerlaſting life,</hi> to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way doubting, and to eſtabliſh our harts in an aſſured poſſeſſion thereof.</p>
               <p>No leſſe gaine ariſeth, by remembring the Lords couenant which hee maketh with his, &amp; how it is a couenant <hi>euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 32. 40</note> not for a time: and with ſuch as he maketh it, he giueth them grace, &amp; <hi>put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his feare in their hearts,</hi> that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer depart from him. <hi>Ier.</hi> 32. 40.</p>
               <p>Laſtly we may eſtabliſh our thoghts vpon the ground of a mans ſaluation: <hi>The foundation of God remaineth ſure,</hi> his <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2 19.</note> free mercie in Chriſt Ieſus chuſing ſome to euerlaſting life: no inducement in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: before we haue being, our end is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: nothing good foreſeene in vs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God: no way in vs is there cauſe at all of our happines, but begun fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods free good pleaſure, and eſtabliſhed in Chriſt; out of whom wee may not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any leaſt thing that may be benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to worke mans ſaluation, or to procure good to vs, which is not freely giuen of God, and obtained by Chriſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:23753:28"/> alone without any reſpect of vs at all. Whence, a penitent ſinner may thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably reaſon; Gods I was, before I had my beeing, in my beeing by corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature hee found me his enemy, yet did he not hate me, but ſhewed his mercie vnto me: he ordained me before the world, that cauſed him in time to bring me into the world: my ſinnes did not hinder the paſſage of mercy, becauſe in Chriſt he would be ſatisfied for mee: I will therefore ſurely conclude, that God remaining one in mercie, &amp; Chriſt Ieſus alway wel-pleaſing to his father, the cauſe of my ſaluation beeing ſtil one and the ſame, I will not doubt damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for falles of infirmity; when as Gods mercie and Chriſtes merit preuented the ſame in mine obſtinate ſtanding in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Thus by meditation may wee ſtrengthen and ſettle our ſelues in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to be ſaued. Praiſe the Lord.</p>
               <p>It pleaſeth God to afford his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <note place="margin">By diuine inſpiration</note> more in muſing on heauenly comforts, then when mens thoughts are beſtowed vpon other things: he aydeth them with his ſpirit, who openeth our eies to ſee the ſecrets of the kingdome of God, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:23753:28"/> to <hi>know the things that are giuen vs of God:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 12. Rom. 8. 10.</note> who giueth teſtimony to our ſpirit, that we are the children of God: which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes alſo is true and not lying, (as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith). This is the ſpirit of adoption, by which we are ſealed; and the earneſt which he giueth, when he taketh vs to be his. Haue I then the ſpirit of Chriſt? I am Chriſts; and in him there is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1.)</p>
               <p>Now leaſt we be miſled by Satans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, and take it for the holy ſpirits in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, <note place="margin">By ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. How to know the perſwaſion of Gos ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, from Sathans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion. ſee Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. 5. 11. 15. 16.</note> there is a third thing to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that is ſanctification. For if we haue the ſpirit of God, we are led by it; wee walke not after the fleſh, but ſauour the things of the ſpirit, which quickneth our mortall bodies; by it wee doe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the deedes of the fleſh; by it we are without feare, and dare come to God &amp; cry Abba father: this ſpirit helpeth our infirmities in prayer, it maketh requeſt for vs with ſighes that cannot be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. This is the witneſſing of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with our ſpirit: it is not a bare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a true perſwaſion from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall graces which it worketh in vs, cauſing vs to liue in newneſſe of life.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:23753:29"/> This ſpirit witneſſeth not to our ſpirit, if it bee adulterous, nor to our drunken ſpirit, nor to our ſweating, lying, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous and rayling ſpirit, nor to our prophane and mocking ſpirit (if ſuch we be) that we are the ſonnes of God: no, no, for our conſcience telleth vs, that ſuch are the ſonnes of the Diuel, and all perſwaſion of ſaluation is but Sathans deceiueable deluſions to ſecure vs in ſin.</p>
               <p>The holie ſpirit will not ſay wee are coheires with Chriſt &amp; certaine of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whilſt we walke on in wickednes; hee teacheth in the ſcripture the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, and ſheweth that <hi>there is no peace</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſai. 57. 21. Pſal. 9. 17. Mat. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>to the wicked, they ſhall go into hell, and all the workers of in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Therefore let vs not think otherwiſe, but it is the ſpirit of Sathan, and not the holy Ghoſt, that worketh an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of any certaintie of ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation, whilſt wee liue vnſanctified, in our thoughts, vnchanged in our ſpeech, and vnreformed in our conuerſation.</p>
               <p>We ſee, that aſſurnace may bee had by the foreſaid meanes, it muſt make vs ſtriue by theſe means for it: which if we obtaine; O bleſſed are we, ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is come vnto vs, the comfort of all
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:23753:29"/> comforts. Through this aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, thogh we fall, we riſe againe, and doubt not of <note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which ariſe vnto vs by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> mercie when we repent. We ioy to heate of death, becauſe we are perſwaded to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all; we feare not man, that onely can kill the bodie, for that our ſoules are in ſafety: This maketh vs deſire to bee taken from hence, and to be diſſolued: This maketh vs loue and long after the comming of the Lord Ieſus; ſaying <hi>how long Lord, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lord, O come Lord Ieſus, come quickly:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Reue. 6. 10. 22. 20.</note> This (to conclude) freeth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all dread of any euil that may befall vs, from the rigour of the law: it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not condemne vs; if it do, Chriſt Ieſus acquiteth vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of conſcience: it dare not accuſe vs; if it do, Chriſt will ſpeak for vs: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deaths ſting &amp; dead ſtroke; it hath not right to rule ouer vs: if it do, its but a while, Chriſt hath got the victory: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fierce wrath of the Iudge in the laſt day, when he ſhal be before vs, Angels on one hand; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels on an other; about vs the world bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; in million<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds conſcience accuſing, crying out to the mountains to couer them; hell gaping ready to deuoure all to whome Chriſt ſhall ſay, <hi>Go ye curſed with the Diuell &amp; his angels:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:23753:30"/> But what terrour can this be to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, aſſured of life? none at all. The Diuels cannot daunt vs, the repentant hath his pardon: Angels will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime vs, they here haue waited vpon vs: God will acknowledge vs, we haue his ſpirit the aſſurance of his loue: And can the Iudge Ieſus Chriſt condemne vs, who is our ſauiour, and hath by his death acquited vs?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, we are freed from the horrour of hell, where Diuels &amp; damned ghoſts bee; where paine is endleſs; the place darkneſſe; the perſons puniſhed with fire and brimſtone remedileſſe; their noiſe is hydeous; weeping and wayling for time loſt and not recouerable; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; lamentably crying for time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and paines intollerable, they gnaſh with their teeth one vpon an other, their conſcience accuſing &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntinually tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting: They languiſh with paine, wiſhing to die: but they ſhall remaine and euer bee, though liueleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, that their torment may be endleſs.</p>
               <p>Sithen aſſurance of ſaluation here deliuereth vs from the dread of theſe things, what cauſe haue wee to vſe all
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:23753:30"/> meanes to get ſo great and vnſpeakable a good? Oh let vs then meditate ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, pray for the ſpirit ardently, and liue here conſcionably, that wee may bee therefore certaine of our ſaluation, and ſo liue eternally, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Your calling and election ſure.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> YOur calling, that is, which you haue taſted of by the miniſtry &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Gods word; giue all diligence to make it ſure, ſee it be not vocall, but effectuall; not a calling to an externall profeſſion, but to an internall ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bloſſoming forth in good workes. Make this ſure: but doe you aske how? <note place="margin">How to make our calling ſure.</note> by good workes, that is by knowing, feeling, and euer retaining ſuch graces as are Gods good workes, wrought in a man effectually called, at the time of his conuerſion. The true knowledge of <note place="margin">By know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> the Lord Ieſus is a worke of God in a mans conuerſion (<hi>Act.</hi> 9. 5. 18) who ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the eies of the blinde, turneth men <note place="margin">Ier. 31. 33</note> from Satan to God, from darknes to the light (<hi>Act.</hi> 26. 18) True ſight of ſinne, with humiliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſame is an other: <note place="margin">Humiliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:23753:31"/> when certaine were conuerted, they ſaw their ſinnes, confeſſed them, &amp; left them. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 37. and. 19. 18. Faith in the Lord Ieſus is an other; the firſt grace of one truly ſtanding in the ſtate of grace: for he is not by the word called effectually, that beleeueth not faithfully; for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring bring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beleeuing: and ſuch as are <note place="margin">Rom. 10, 14</note> called of God, beleeue in the ſonne (<hi>Ioh. 8. 30. Act.</hi> 8. 37). After this followeth a plyable hart to obey God: the ſtony heart remoued, in ſtead thereof God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a heart of fleſh, yielding ſubiection to God, his word and ſpirit. (<hi>Eze.</hi> 36. 26. 27.) This will make <hi>Paul</hi> going to perſecute, ignorant of Chriſt, after one queſtion made and anſwered, (<hi>Who art thou Lord? I am Ieſus whom thou perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteſt</hi>), <note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> in the next place to ſay, <hi>Lord what wilt thou that I doe?</hi> not making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more reſiſtance. This made <hi>Dauid</hi> ready to do any thing willingly at Gods bidding; yea, and it cauſeth vs humbly to condiſcend to his good pleaſure, and ſay with <hi>Ezechias,</hi> The word of the Lord is good; with <hi>Ely,</hi> Its the Lord let him do what ſeemeth him good; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with Ieſus Chriſt, Father not my w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut thy will be fulfilled. Laſtly, the <note place="margin">Vnion with Chriſt.</note> Lord worketh an vnion of hart &amp; ſpirit with other in Chriſt <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. 32. 40</note>: wherby it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:23753:31"/> to paſſe that we do conioine in one toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one with another: thus, <hi>Act.</hi> 2, 42, the church is ſet forth, &amp; in that verſe are 8: graces of the Church; their conſtancy in this word <hi>they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued,</hi> in the next word <note place="margin">The eight graces of the Church.</note> 
                  <hi>daily</hi> their ſeruencie, with <hi>one acord</hi> their vnitie, <hi>in the Temple</hi> their audacitie, in other words following, their charity, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, alacrity &amp; ſincerity, vnto which by the voice of Chriſt they were called, and wherewith we muſt be endued and therein continue, elſe we cannot make our calling ſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Therfore ſuch as remaine in blindnes, ſuch as are not humbled for ſins, neuer came to the ſight of them, neuer ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ſought for pardon for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but liue in their luſts, &amp; loden themſelues with i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity; ſuch as giue not credyt to the word of God, beleeue not his faithfull meſſengers; ſuch as be obſtinate &amp; ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, refuſing the eaſie yoke of Chriſt, or to draw with the godly therin, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mocke at holy exerciſes, raile on ſuch as deſire to pleaſe God, endeuor to bring trouble vniuſtly vpon them: theſe though they be come to externall bare profeſſion, yet ſithen they are not come to reformation, by their calling, they cannot bee ſure that they are ſaued:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:23753:32"/> they may liue in the Church, but yet are none of it; tares they be, but none of the Lords wheat: they are in that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the many called, but not of the fewe that ſhall bee ſaued: they are like the gueſt comming in without his wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment, whom the Lord one day will command to bee bound hand and foote, and to be caſt into vtter darkenes, where is weeping and wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calling and election.</hi> In the order of <note place="margin">Expoſition.</note> cauſes, election is before vocation: for therefore are we called, becauſe wee are elected. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. but in ſearching out our ſaluation, according to the work wroght vpon vs, and the ſame felt in vs, calling muſt be before election; ſo is it in iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and ſanctification, that is before this, if we note the cauſe and effect; but this muſt wee finde in vs, before the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for our owne aſſurance: ſanctified we be in our owne perſons, but iuſtified onely in Chriſts righteouſnes: Election is ſecret in God, and by effectuall voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion knowne and reuealed to vs, and the firſt ſenſible worke of GOD vpon vs touching ſoules ſafety: God commeth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:23753:32"/> forward, beginning in and from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to doe vs good; wee, to find this, muſt goe backward, from within our ſelues, by ſanctification to iuſtification, by vocation to election, and thence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our eternall ſaluation. Therefore <note place="margin">Eſay, 43. 1.</note> is it that here the holy Ghoſt hath thus ſet downe the words, and the like elſe where. The wiſedome of God doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without iuſt cauſe: he breaks not order, as ignorant of order: neither ſets downe matter as miſtaken; but euer to teach vs from thence ſomewhat, which by the help of Gods ſpirit we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding may further to ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> From this order firſt wee learne, how to make ſure our election, if wee haue made ſure our vocation. There is no doubt of the former, where wee make certaine the latter: and hee that cannot finde himſelfe called, cannot poſſibly be truly perſwaded, that he is one of the elect: for he hath not the next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate worke of God following electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; going before iuſtification. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to know our election, watch for our <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 30.</note> calling, follow the meanes, the miniſtry and preaching of Gods word; the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:23753:33"/> means to bring men to Chriſt. It pleaſeth him by the fooliſhnes thereof to <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 21. Rom. 1. 16</note> ſaue them that beleeue. It is the power of God to ſaluation: where this is careleſly neglected, ſuch ſhall finde no other means to be ſaued; and ſuch as perſecute it, may feare iuſtly to be damned.</p>
               <p>Sythen our election is made ſure by our calling, and our calling confirmed to vs, as is ſaid; I neede not ſay more of this: yet becauſe the word affordeth vs more marks to ſettle our ſelues in better aſſurance, a word thereof or two, alſo.</p>
               <p>Our election is further made ſure by <note place="margin">Markes of election.</note> other markes of the elect, if we find them in vs, &amp; they euer remain vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: which is, to be ſanctified (1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 2) fruitfull in good things, (<hi>Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 16) ſequeſtred from the world (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. 6. &amp; 15. 19) a note which is notto be loued of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, perſeuerance (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 16) following after Chriſt (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. 28) without departing from him (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 19) loue to the godly, (1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 14) faith in Gods promiſes, and a holy reuerence to Gods ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, his word and ſacraments: and he that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth herein vnto the end ſhalbe ſaued.</p>
               <p>Again this order obſerued preuenteth <note place="margin">Another vſe, how to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the abuſe of that holy doctrine of Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> preſumption in the doctrine of predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:23753:33"/> If I be ordained to a certain end, ſaith the wicked wight, and that Gods decree muſt ſtand, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> its no matter how I liue, its all one to ſerue God or to liue as I like beſt: if I be ordained to be ſaued I ſhall not be damned; if to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, its in vaine to hope for heauen. It is true that Gods decree ſhall ſtand, but its a deſperat ſpirits collection, to hold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we may liue as we liſt. Election is ſecret, &amp; ſo Gods decree, his will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuealed: whence wee may gather no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but as the ſcripture, the written word, his reuealed will teacheth. It a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoucheth predeſtination, &amp; Gods vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable decree: but it ſaith, Work out your ſaluation with feare &amp; trembling, &amp; ſo beareth downe preſumption. It tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of reprobation, but not to make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſperat: for touching euery mans ſelf in particular, he is to hope the beſt, &amp; may ſay with the king of Niniuie, <hi>Who can tell if God wil turne and repent and turne away</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ionah. 3. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fierce wrath that we periſh not?</hi> Euery man in particular by the reuealed will of God is commanded to liue religiouſly, and ſo bound to beleeue his owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: this word are wee to liue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſtriue we muſt to go in at the ſtrait gate, hoping to finde paſſage. <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:23753:34"/> No man is to iudge himſelfe to be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whilſt he here liueth in the way to be ſaued, if hee wilfully refuſe not the meanes. None will ſo reaſon from Gods decree concerning the bodie; It is ſaid, that <hi>mans daies are determined,</hi> the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <note place="margin">Iob. 14. 5.</note> of his monthes are with God, &amp; that hee hath appointed the bounds which man cannot paſſe: who hereupon will thus reſolue? then will I be careleſſe of my life, I will neither eate nor drinke, nor vſe meanes of life, becauſe I cannot liue beyond my appointed time. Herein is none ſo madde; but for all this, will vſe the meanes which God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to liue by, for that his time is kept ſecret from him, and onely knowne to God: euen ſo ſhould we do in this caſe, for our ſoules, vſe the meanes to liue for euer, ſo are wee commanded: this wee know; but whither God hath reiected vs before the end, we know not: neither may any one herein make ſearch, but vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand in ſobrietie that which is meet, obey what is commanded, beleeue what is promiſed, and ceaſe to imagined deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, and ſinne not preſumptuouſly, &amp; hope well in the end. And ſo ſhall wee
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:23753:34"/> make ſure to ourſelues that which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer certaine and vnchangeable with God: this note. And thus much for the exhortation: the reaſon follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For;</hi> a note of a reaſon of the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Enim.</note> which goeth before, concluded as an vſe from the former arguments: a gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall obſeruation in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction, to be well marked; there is differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>for</hi> &amp; <hi>therefore;</hi> both in this verſe: <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Quaprop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> 
                  <hi>for</hi> ſheweth the reaſon of that which go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before, &amp; <hi>therfore</hi> concludeth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what from the antecedent by neceſſarie conſequent. The thing chiefly herein to <note place="margin">What to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as the doctrine, from the Apoſtles practiſe.</note> be marked is, that the Apoſtle neither ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth to practiſe, but vpon mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold inſtructions before; neither endeth the vſe in the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo further reaſon why: Thus he guardeth before and behinde his words, vrging by reaſon as did <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> and our Sauiour, to well doing; that ſo they might take place. He well kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w mens ſlownes to practiſe, and that they neede haue good grounds laid before them to build thereon the exhortation to obey, and alſo reaſons after to perſwade ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:23753:35"/> All of vs naturally affect to know; but without loue to doe: whence it is, that men vnregenerate can run to heare ſermons of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies, (ſuch as preach by ſentences, that can now and then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie fantaſie with ſome noueltie) &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne with their mouthes full of praiſe, applauding the perſon, who hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ailed happily to preſſe all to practiſe, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of life. Learning is Gods good gift, eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a ſingular bleſſing, wit and memorie rare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auours, to make men amongſt men honourable: but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe be employed in the miniſtry to make men vertuous, as the Apoſtle doth here, Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in his Epiſtles, &amp; as the Prophets did, and profound <hi>I ſee</hi> with his admirable eloquence, we may heare, learne, ſpeake and admire, as without obedience, ſo without hope of that heauenly inheritance. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Therefore let our wit for inuention of reaſons, our learning to collect ſound grounds, bee guides to our liberty of ſpeech in vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and this gift end in exhortation to good workes, and to make men zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. So deale we faithfully, the people ſhall reape benefite, and we that preach
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:23753:35"/> gaine great comfort by our labours in winning ſoules, which onely we ought to aime at, and therein reioice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If yee doe theſe things.</hi> The conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall word, <hi>If,</hi> in the Original is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, nor the perſon <hi>Yee;</hi> the words <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Haec facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s.</hi>
                  </note> beeing, <hi>Theſe doing:</hi> but the perſon and the condition is neceſſarily vnderſtood, and therefore expreſſed in the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion very fitly: which wee following in the diuiſion of the Text, do take as granted implied in the text. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> Whence we learne, that God ſo promiſeth aſſurance of ſaluation, as we haue care in vs, to liue well and to keepe the condition: the one cheareth the heart; but leaſt we be wanton, the other is added to keepe vs in awe: but neuertheleſſe, here may we not thinke therefore, that Gods gift is not free, or that it is changeable, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we make it ſure: no ſuch end of the condition.</p>
               <p>GOD firſt beſtoweth freely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing on mans p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t: ſo hee gaue <hi>Adam</hi> firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preheminence ouer all his other creatures, and placed <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26</note> him freely in Paradiſe, without any
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:23753:36"/> forenamed condition, then afterward expreſſeth he mans duetie to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not as a cauſe procuring or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing <note place="margin">Preuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> goodnes, but as an effect of loue in harty thankfulnes, or as a token and ſigne by which we may know God to be ſo long in vs, and with vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Chriſt, of his mere good pleaſure; <hi>Adam</hi> neuer once deſiring, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 16.</note> that fauour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt came in the appointed time, and was freely giuen for vs, of loue in mercie and compaſſion; all this done truely, fully, and abſolutely on Gods part: yet after commanded hee the obedience of faith, and promiſeth ſaluation, with condition of beleeuing, <note place="margin">Mark. 16. 16.</note> on our behalfe; not as a cauſe, but as a ſigne by which men may know to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt is freely giuen of the father, and in him haue eternall life.</p>
               <p>It is then, as if <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eter</hi> had ſaid; If ye do theſe things, you thereby haue a true ſigne and token from God of his loue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting and ſhall neuer fall from him: the like is that in the <hi>Pſalme</hi> 15, 6. He that doth theſe things ſhall neuer fall.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Therefore to attaine to the benefite of this promiſe, let vs here looke to the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:23753:36"/> condition; which is, carefully to exerciſe our ſelues in theſe vertues afore menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. Firſt well doing, keepeth vs from euill; euery gift of grace is a ſentinell to <note place="margin">Firſt reaſon.</note> watch againſt the oppoſite vice, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entrance to the heart. Hold ſobriety, drunkenneſſe getteth no place: chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty preſerueth from diſhoneſty; feruency of ſpirit cannot abide luke-warme to lodge with it; light liketh not of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; righteouſnes of vnrighteouſnes; knowledge of Ignorance; nor godly humility of Sathanicall pride and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie; &amp; looke how much we haue of goodnes, ſo much aduantage get we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt wickednes: euery vertue aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it ſelfe and keeping it proper place in the ſoule, when the contrary vice aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aileth it; Sathan ſuggeſting, and by outward obiects inticing the heart to yield thereunto.</p>
               <p>Secondly, theſe vertues are the fruits <note place="margin">Second rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> of the ſpirit: whence a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, that hee hath the ſpirit; and hee which hath this hath Chriſt, without whom no redemption, no ſaluation. Theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are pleaſant flowers, which gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, are aſweete noſegay to garniſh our
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:23753:37"/> ſoules with, for the Lords delight. They are the guariſon of the holy Ghoſt lodged in the ſoule, to keepe out ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, as yet haue not entrance, and to bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ill motions of the heart, daily ariſing, that we periſh not. Thus much of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in generall. But let vs, if but briefly weigh them in particular; and the goodneſs of them, will more allure vs to loue them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> is the crowne of graces, and the <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of ſeuerall vertues: Faith.</note> roote of vertues; it maketh morality by the lawe, to turne into Chriſtianity by the Goſpell: without it we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not pleaſe God: by it we make the word preached profitable: and by it wee apprehend Chriſt, who ſatisfieth iuſtice, aſſwageth wrath, bringeth downe mercy, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen gates are open for vs, and wee enter, and take poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vertue,</hi> integrity; the generall word <note place="margin">Vertue.</note> for a ſpeciall, which is the breſt-plate of righteouſneſs, keeping countenance without bluſhing; it is the ioy of the ſpirit, and maketh men bold as a Lyon: it dare anſwere at the barre to the beſt, &amp; ſay truely, Not guilty; it deſireth tryall, and therein alwaies getteth approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and credite of euerie cauſe; not fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:23753:37"/> malice, though lying and deceipt manage the matter with all the friends that may be made: it maketh man looke vp chearefully vnto God, and ſo reſteth quiet in his owne innocency.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Knowledge;</hi> it is the candle of the ſoule, <note place="margin">Knowledge.</note> the rule of actions, the diſcerner of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Iudge of controuerſies, the guide of affection, the bridle for the tongue, and the life of conſcience, and the firſt <hi>motor</hi> to obedience: it ſaueth from errour, condemneth hereſie, and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alwaies for verity, if peruerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit turne it not into ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Temperance;</hi> knowledge is the firſt <hi>motor,</hi> this is moderator: it qualifieth &amp; <note place="margin">Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance.</note> allayeth extreames; it is in nothing vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: it preuenteth liking before looke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; it ſtoppeth rage of luſt, and bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth appetite; it diſcuſſeth cauſes with deliberation; it ordereth words with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; hot ſpirits by it may expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late iniuries done without contention: by it, knowledge telleth his tale wiſely, and integrity is bold with ſafety.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Patience,</hi> is the mother of peace, a ſtrong back to beare all burthens; it <note place="margin">Patience.</note>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:23753:38"/> ſaith nothing to reuiling ſpeeches, and is not an auenger of priuate iniuries: it waiteth for accompliſhment of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes long; it is the daughter of humility, and the ſafe conductor of integrity: by it we poſſeſſe our ſoules, and the enemy getteth not aduantage; it is neuer in want, dwelling alwaies with content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> this is the chiefe goodneſs; <note place="margin">Godlineſs.</note> by ſenſe we are better then the creature ſenſleſs; by reaſon, better then the beaſt; by religion, better then man onely ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reaſon; but godlyneſſe is the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of religion: it is the eſpeciall fruit of faith, ſincerities comfort, the principall end of all learning, the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all knowledge, the creatures admiration, and here to the mightieſt in the world their higheſt exaltation: god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is great gaine; it hath the promiſe of this life, and of the life to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brotherly kindnes,</hi> the procurer of loue, <note place="margin">Brotherly kindneſs.</note> the diſpoſition of the heart, to doe good to other; it graunteth fauour to euerie frined; it liueth euer in charity; it is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and lendeth, it is ready to doe pleaſures, and liberall without delay; it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:23753:38"/> is the goodnes of a mercifull heart, plia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to euery good worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Loue</hi> is the laſt, which is the fruit of <note place="margin">Loue. 1. Cor. 13.</note> brotherly kindneſs; the grace which the Apoſtle ſo highly extolles, and neede not here to be ſtoode vpon: but I will conclude it, with that abſolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, that Loue is the fulfilling of the lawe. And thus we ſee, what reaſon there is for vs to haue theſe excellent vertues, and to exerciſe our ſelues in them, that we may neuer fall: otherwiſe we are without certainty of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and tokens of eternall comfort.</p>
               <p>The looſe and careleſs liuer, the vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <note place="margin">Reproofe to the leud &amp; vicious.</note> and leud man is heere vtterly left hopeleſs; he cannot looke for heauen; the ſcripture tels him, that there hee hath no enheritance: he that committeth ſin is of the Diuel, the reward is death, the <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3. 8 Rom. 6. 23. Pſal. 9. 17.</note> wicked ſhall goe into hell and all the people that forget God. If any, for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſatisfaction, would know for what ſinnes in particular death is threatned, and for which men are denyed heauen; they ſhall finde, that euery ſinne vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of procureth damnation; but it pleaſeth the holy Ghoſt to number vp
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:23753:39"/> many particulars: the places not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to be mentioned, to ſee and conſider of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 29. 30, are reckoned vp <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 29. 30. recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp 23 ſins.</note> three and twenty ſins, <hi>Vnrighteouſneſs, fornication, wickedneſs, couetouſneſs, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs, full of enuie, of murther, of debate, of deceipt, taking all things in euill part, whiſperers, backbiters, haters of God, doers of wrong, proud, boaſters, inuenters of euill things, diſobedient to pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, without vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t breakers, without naturall affection, ſuch as can neuer be appeaſed, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe;</hi> for which, not onely they that doe them, but alſo that fauour them that doe them are worthy of death. In 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. 10. are ſet downe ten kindes <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 9. 10. ten ſorts of vicious perſons.</note> of vicious perſons; <hi>Fornicators, idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, adulterers, wantons, buggerers, theeues, couetous, drunkerds, raylers, and extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> which ſhall not inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. In <hi>Galathians.</hi> 5. 19. 20. <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 19 20, workes of the fleſh 17.</note> are particularized ſeauenteene workes of the fleſh; <hi>Adulterie, fornication, vncleanneſſe, wantonneſſe, idolatry, witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, hatred, debate, emulations, wrath, contentions, ſeditions, hereſies, enuie, murthers, drunkenneſſe, gluttonie:</hi> which who-ſo doth, ſhall not inherite life.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:23753:39"/> In the ſecond of <hi>Timothie,</hi> 3. 2. 3. 4. 5. are reckoned vp nineteene ſorts of the <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 2. 3 4. 5. Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eteene ſorts of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</note> wicked and vngodly, who will riſe vp in the laſt daies, when times ſhall be perillous: <hi>louers of themſelues, couetous, boasters, proud, curſed ſpeakers, diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to parents, vnthankfull, vnholy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naturall affection, truce breakers, falſe accuſers, intemperate, fierce, no louers at all of them which are good, traytors, headie, hye minded, louers of pleaſures more then louers of God, hauing a ſhewe of godlineſſe but haue denyed the power thereof:</hi> from whom, ſuch as truly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt muſt turne away. In the <hi>Reuelations,</hi> 21. 8. there are eight ſortes threatned with the ſecond death, and <note place="margin">Reu. 21. 8. Eight ſorts.</note> to be tormented in the lake which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with fire and brimſtone: <hi>Feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vnbeleeuing, abhominable, murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, whoremongers, ſorcerers, idolaters, and lyers.</hi> The ſpirit ſaith, <hi>Reuelations,</hi> 21. 20, None defiled ſhall enter into heauen. But our ſauiour in <hi>Mark.</hi> 7. 21. <note place="margin">Mark. 7. 21, 22. are 14.</note> 22. whereto ad <hi>Math.</hi> 15. 19, telleth vs of foureteene euils which defile a man. <hi>Euill thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murthers, thefts, couetouſneſs, wickedneſs,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:23753:40"/> deceipts, vncleanneſſe, a wicked eie, backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, pride, fooliſhnes, falſe teſtimonies, and ſlaunders.</hi> And therefore ſuch ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God and of Chriſt. Theſe ſix be the chiefeſt places <note place="margin">Sixtie and od diſtinct ſins menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in ſix places.</note> in all the newe teſtament, ſetting forth ſo many particular vicious perſons &amp; hate ful ſinnes: wherein albeit, in ſome the ſame be againe repeated; yet in all, there be diſtinct and ſeuerall in number three ſcore and odde, beſides other ſinnes mentioned in ſeuerall places elſewhere, which without repenting of and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, depriue men of life and ſaluation. If any of vs yet bleſſe our ſelues in our hearts hearing ſo plainly theſe things, then conſider what the Lord ſaith to ſuch, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 20. Great and fierce is the wrath of God againſt ſuch a one. <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider thou that readeſt, &amp; preſume not.</note> Firſt he ſaith plainly that he will not be mercifull vnto him: ſecondly, that his wrath and his iealouſie ſhall ſmoke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that man: thirdly, that euery curſe written in the booke ſhall light vpon him: as if the curſes in the former chapter mentioned, aboue forty and three, were too few to plague ſuch a preſumptuous Catiffe; but all the curſes in the booke
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:23753:40"/> muſt light vpon him; and laſtly, the Lord will roote out his name from vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſeparate him vnto euil out of all the tribes of Iſrael. What is this, but to depriue him of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of ſaincts, and to pronounce ſentence of damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt him, in the laſt day? O ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou that heareſt conſider, as ſome that haue heard it: If Gods truth herein may be taken for truth with thee, if the anger of God may preuaile to feare thee, if the fierce-wrath of God may terrifie thee, if all the curſes in Gods booke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced may worke any dread in thee; hope not vainly of mercy whilſt thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt vnrepentant of any ſinne: let not conceipt of pardon make thee put farre from thee the euil day; for, ſurely elſe in one ſinne thou ſhalt bee puniſhed, and thine end confuſion: marke, vnderſtand and pray.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye doe.</hi> The condition is, if wee doe <note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> theſe things; not heare, learne, profeſſe them: doing is that which hath with God approbation; after our deedes ſhall we be rewarded, <hi>Rom. 2. 6. Math. 16. 27. 2. Cor. 5. 10. Math. 25. 35. 42.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs hope well, if we be doers: here
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:23753:41"/> is approued the reading in the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, make your calling and election ſure <hi>by good vvorkes:</hi> for the reaſon of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance here, is from deedes: <hi>If ye doe</hi> theſe things; that is, If ye ſhew the fruits of theſe eight Chriſtian vertues in good works, ye ſhall neuer fall.</p>
               <p>This is ſeriouſly to be noted; for that moſt thinke to haue eternall life, and yet are no doers of theſe things; but vpon falſe euidences claime a right in that which without good workes they ſhall neuer enioy. For as aſſurance here, is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition, that we be doers: ſo there is nothing otherwiſe approued, though wee doe bring in many things to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <note place="margin">Eighteene deceiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to clame hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by, without good workes.</note> vs otherwiſe. 1 <hi>Thou art baptiſed,</hi> what then? <hi>Neither circumciſion auaileth any thing, nor vncircumciſion, but the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the commandements.</hi> 1. Cor. 7. 19, <hi>but a nevv creature.</hi> Gal. 6. 15. 2 <hi>Thou art a hearer:</hi> what of this? <hi>Not the hearers but the doers of the Lavv ſhall be iuſtified.</hi> Rom 2. 13. He that heareth &amp; doeth not, is a foole. Math. 7. 26, &amp; deceiueth himſelfe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames. 1. 22. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Thou knovveſt the vvil of God.</hi> neuer a whit better without obedience, <hi>thou ſhalt be beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvith many ſtripes,</hi> Luke
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:23753:41"/> 12. 47. thou increaſeſt thy ſinne. Ia. 4. 17. and the ſcripture ſaith: <hi>Hee that ſaith hee knoweth me, &amp; keepeth not my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts is a lyer &amp; there is no truth in him. Thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueſt:</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſo do the diuels, and more alſo; they feare &amp; tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, which thou doſt not &amp; ſo art worſe then a diuell: but if thou haſt faith, <hi>ſhew it by thy works,</hi> Iam. 2. 8: els its dead, and thou a dry tree for the fire. <hi>Thou loueſt God:</hi> then hearken: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>This is the loue of God, that we keepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements.</hi> 1. Ioh. 5. 3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <hi>Thou hopeſt yet well;</hi> but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe at all: <hi>for he that hath this hope in him purgeth himſelf as he is pure.</hi> 1. Iohn. 3. 3 <hi>Thou feareſt God:</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> then thou muſt ad with <note place="margin">Eccle. 12. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> to it, <hi>feare God &amp; keep his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements;</hi> for they are neuer ſeparated. <hi>Thou doſt profeſs Chriſt the Lord:</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> ſo did the diuels; but, <hi>Not euery one that ſaith vnto me Lord, lord, ſhal enter in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the kingdome of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 21</note> 
                  <hi>heauen, but he that doth the wil of my father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Thou canſt preach:</hi> a ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding braſſe &amp; tinkling Cymball with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes: many will ſay in the day of the Lord that they haue prophecied and caſt out diuels, yet as workers of iniquitie, God will reiect them, &amp; ſend them packing with diuels. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 23.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:23753:42"/> 
                  <hi>Thou vſeſt to pray:</hi> but where no practiſe is, there is but hypocriſie; <hi>Let euery one that calleth on the name of Chriſt, depart from iniquitie.</hi> 2. Tim. 3. 19: elſe may we call, but God will not heare vs. Iſai. 1. 15. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                  <hi>Thou happily doſt faſt:</hi> but it is no faſt that God requireth, without obedience. Iſa. 58. 6. 7. <hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Thou commeſt orderly to the Church;</hi> more of faſhion then of ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without doing Gods will: God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth it not at thine hands to treade in his courts, whilſt thou liueſt vnreformed <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ai.</hi> 1. 12. Thou makeſt the houſe of God a denne of theeues. Ier. 7. 10, 11. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Thou payeſt duely tithes and offerings, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt the appointed daies to keepe them holy:</hi> Without ſubiection to Gods will and commandement; he is wearied with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he cannot ſuffer them, and to thy ſelfe they are iniquity, Iſa. 1. 13. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt often good motions and flaſhes, making thee wiſh well to thy ſelfe;</hi> ſo had &amp; did <hi>Balam</hi> that wicked wiſard. Thou haſt more then ſo, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 
                  <hi>Thou canſt be moued to weepe now and then:</hi> ſo could <hi>Saule. 1. Sam.</hi> 24. 17, and <hi>Eſau</hi> found no place to repentance, though hee ſought the bleſſing with teares. Heb. 12, 17. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 
                  <hi>Thou canſt bow at the</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:23753:42"/> 
                  <hi>name of Ieſus and often be made ſad by the word, and canſt in countenance and geſture carry thy ſelfe religiouſly:</hi> So Diuels did fall downe and worſhip Chriſt. Felix, he at the word trembled, and <hi>Ahab</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelfe before the Lord. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 21 27. 29. Scribes and Phariſes looked ſad, and were in ſhew full of grauitie &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. <hi>Iudas</hi> did ſhewe reuerence to Chriſt and ſaid, Haile maſter: yet Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels are damned ſpirits: <hi>Felix</hi> a heathen miſcreant, <hi>Ahab</hi> an accurſed Idolater, who had ſold himſelfe to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly in the ſight of the Lord, Scribes and Phariſees notorious hypocrites, and ſworne enemies of Chriſt, and <hi>Iudas</hi> was a diuell and a traytor. And therfore its not bowing nor becking, nor looke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſowrely vpon the matter, neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny geſture or fawning faſhions, that can without holy obedience make men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelues truly of their happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> 
                  <hi>Thou doſt ſpeake vvell of God and his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, praiſe them and commend them as they deſerue:</hi> So did the Herodians com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Chriſt, with moſt high commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, <note place="margin">Mark. 12. 14.</note> ſo as they could not ſpeake bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:23753:43"/> So did the Pythoniſt ſo commend <note place="margin">Act. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> as no man can ſay more of the worthieſt ſeruants of God, nor more truly; yet the one ſorte Chriſt his enemies and the other poſſeſſed with a diuell. Good words then cannot go away with it: wee may like Sermons now and then, wee may commend the preachers of Gods word, and yet be out of the ſtate of grace: to conclude, <hi>Thou muſeſt of thy good meaning, though thou dost amiſſe:</hi> but remember, <hi>Vzza</hi> had <note place="margin">2. Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 6. 7.</note> no ill meaning, To ſaue the arke from falling, yet againſt Gods word; for which it coſt him his life. Meane well, but let the word rule thee, and liue thereafter, and then doubt not to finde peace for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This I haue vrged, thus much: firſt to pull downe the preſumption of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and time ſeruing proteſtants; and ſecondly againſt the Papiſts, who doe ſay we allow not good workes, but do make our religion a religion of liberty &amp; of faith without workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doing.</hi> The word is in the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Doctrine. Exod. 3.</note> to ſhew that onely preſent doers may looke for a bleſſing; God is <hi>I am;</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:23753:43"/> not I was, or wil be: ſo muſt wee all bee now, that which wee ought to be, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15, the queſtion pronounced in the firſt verſe, <hi>Lord who ſhall dwel in thy tabernacle,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſhall reſt in thy holy hill?</hi> the anſwere is made in the time preſent, he that <hi>walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, worketh</hi> &amp; <hi>ſpeaketh;</hi> to ſhew, that ſuch (as is in the verſe 5) <hi>ſhall neuer be moued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſerues to reproue two ſortes of <note place="margin">Vſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt backſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> perſons: firſt ſuch as haue done wel, men of the time paſt, but haue falne away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which they were; theſe are hopeleſs of heauen, except they returne againe, becauſe they haue loſt that which ſhold giue them aſſurance, Well doing; alſo for that the ſcripture ſaith, that ſuch can looke for nothing but vengeance: <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 10. Therefore if we haue left off, either in whole or in part, let vs returne to our firſt loue, elſe wee ſhall neuer be able to <note place="margin">Reue. 2 5</note> anſwere it; for what do wee diſlike, that maketh vs not either at all religious, or not ſo much as we haue ben? the <hi>Author,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Nothing in religion ſhould cauſe vs to leaue it.</note> that is God, the euerliuing God: <hi>matter,</hi> that is Ieſus Chriſt, verity &amp; holineſs &amp; vertue: <hi>maner,</hi> that is, in ſpirit &amp; truth: the <hi>end,</hi> that is Gods glory &amp; our eternal ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafety: wee therefore haue no cauſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:23753:44"/> from religion it ſelfe to leaue it; but the cauſe muſt be found, to be either the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, as in <hi>Iudas:</hi> or in the world, as in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> or the curſed corruption of our fleſh, as in <hi>Salomon,</hi> that hath drawne vs away from God to the Diuell, from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the earth, from the ſpirit to the fleſh, a madde and miſerable exchange: neither let any of vs dreame to bee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for that we haue beene, except wee be as we ought: <hi>For the righteouſneſs of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eze. 33. 12</note> 
                  <hi>the righteous ſhall not deliuer him in the day of his tranſgreſſion. They that forſake the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 17. 13</note> 
                  <hi>Lord ſhall bee confounded: they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him ſhall be vvritten in the earth.</hi> Dogs are ſuch as returne to their vomit, <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> and ſwine to wallow againe in the mire. It will not ſerue <hi>Iudas</hi> turne to ſay, I was an Apoſtle, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Demas</hi> that he was a diſciple, nor <hi>Iehu</hi> that hee had a zeale for the Lord God of hoaſts, nor <hi>Ioaſh</hi> that he was a good king for a time: for then would Sathan ſhuffle in amongſt the reſt &amp; hope to haue a ſhare, &amp; might ſay; Lord let me haue entrance, for I was an Angell in heauen, and ſo neuer were any of them. Brethren know this, If our lamps light goe out before the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:23753:44"/> come, wee may call, the gates being ſhut; but the Lord will ſay, Go ye curſed I know you not. <hi>Therefore let</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>vs take heede brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leaſt at any time, there be in any of vs an euell heart of infidelity to depart from the liuing God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Second ſort are ſuch as be all for the time to come, who haue not yet attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Reproofe to ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre off their ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> to well doing, liuing in hope for hereafter; youth dreaming to ſee olde age, and then thinke they, it is time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to repent, as if it were not ſaid: <hi>Remember thy creatour in the daies of thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>youth, while the euill daies come not, nor the yeares approache wherin thou ſhalt ſay I haue no pleaſure in them.</hi> May we giue the firſt of our life and beſt of our yeares to the ſeruice of Sathan? and thinke wee that God will receiue vs in old age, when ſin hath forſaken vs and not we it? old per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſuppoſe to liue yet longer, and ſo deferre off till the laſt gaſpe, when the generall ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moner hath called them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their death bed; but late and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned repentance is ſeldome true. Our time is not, when we will, but when God doth call; heare we muſt when he <note place="margin">Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. 28</note> ſpeaketh, or elſe hee will not hearken
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:23753:45"/> when we pray. The firſt and beſt is his due; the laſt &amp; worſt of vs, he iuſtly may reiect; our yielding to his will by his word, is voluntarie ſubiection, which he accepteth; but to his wil by his work, is conſtrained obedience for feare of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which he little regardeth. God indeede receiued to mercie the thiefe in the laſt houre; this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be denyed; but yet one onely, though there were two; one, that a true penitent ſinner may not deſpaire; &amp; but one, that vngodly wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>greſſours, may not preſume. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cannot heare the threats of the Law, for feare of deſperation: yet can they willingly run on in ſin, &amp; ſo periſh by preſumption. By this, many millions of thouſands haue fallen headlong downe into hell (remember what Chriſt ſaid of <note place="margin">Luke. 17. 27 28.</note> Sodom &amp; the old world) but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mentioneth few that haue gone to deſtruction by deſperation, <hi>Cain, Sau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, Achitophel,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudas.</hi> Doſt thou hope, to ſpeede as did the good thiefe? and why rather doſt thou not feare to be like the bad thiefe? they both were in one caſe, had the like puniſhment, Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, and death before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nay
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:23753:45"/> the worſe thiefe had the good thieues rebuke &amp; admonition to warne him of his wickedneſs, and to ceaſe to ſin; yet he had no grace to repent. Meanes wil not preuaile in the latter end, where God vouch ſafeth not the gift to amend: If thou doſt perſwade thy ſelfe, that God wil giue thee grace then to repent; thou art deceiued, if now hee offer grace and thou refuſe it. At what time ſo-euer a ſinner doth repent from the bottome of his heart, at that time will GOD free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgiue; but that time is not when we lift, God is not at our beck, but the time is at his call. <hi>To day if ye will heare</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3. Pſal. 95.</note> 
                  <hi>his voice harden not your harts:</hi> to day if we be not ready, wee ſhall be leſſe apt to morrowe: the longer we continue in ſinne the older it is, and the more ſtrength it getteth: It is not as other things, the older the weaker; but daily it groweth ſtronger. If we ſay we can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent when we wil, that is not in our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: and if it be, then if thou doſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent now, and can, thou encreaſeſt ſin by wilfull tranſgreſſion, and ſo makeſt more iuſt thy deſerued damnation.</p>
               <p>Therfore let vs now amend, &amp; not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:23753:46"/> off till he eafter, when at death there is no remedie but either to heauen or to hell, to God or to the diuell; in which caſe men hardly or neuer finde that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort which preſumptuouſly they haue exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted, but doe dye as they haue liued in ſinne without ſenſe or taſte of ioies euerlaſting, prepared onely for the righteous: for, <hi>Hee that beleeueth in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 3. 36</note> 
                  <hi>the ſonne hath euerlaſting life; but he that obeyeth not the ſonne, hath not life, but the wrath of God abideth vpon him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe things:</hi> that is which before he <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> hath mentioned. Men do many things; ſome, the inuentions of their owne braine; ſome, the cuſtome of forefathers; ſome one thing, ſome another: but not <hi>theſe things,</hi> that is which the word tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, <note place="margin">Men do, but not what they ſhould doe.</note> the perfect rule of righteouſnes, from which we may not decline to the right hand or to the left; neither adding thereto nor taking there from: for if wee doe, we keepe not our ſtanding, we loſe our comfort, and wander without our guide we know not whither; ſome who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as Apoſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates; ſome in part perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting obſtinately as hereticks; ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt loue as ſchiſmaticks; and moſt as
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:23753:46"/> lawleſſe, for our liues like prophane <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaus,</hi> will deſpiſe our birthrights and ſell heauen, ſoules health, conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the words of eternal life for a meaſe of pottage, euen for our momentanie pleaſures, luſts and liking in this life.</p>
               <p>Many there are which will doe this <note place="margin">Men doe ſome things but not all things.</note> thing and that thing: theſe ſingularly, but not <hi>theſe things</hi> plurally; when a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſirous of the aſſurance of ſaluation, muſt be ſtudious of euery vertue, which helpeth thereunto: It is the nature of vertue to loue vertue: whence it is that one vertuous man imitateth an other, wherein one ſeeth another to go before him any way. One, two, or few vertues cannot liue, where other vertues are either hated or not ſought after: one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth vpon another, as links in a chaine, and cannot be ſundred; we may not be like <hi>Agryppa</hi> almoſt a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, for almoſt is not a Chriſtian; neither content our ſelues with many things, as <hi>Herod,</hi> though with gladneſs; whilſt we nouriſh ſome ſinne, and be infected but with one notorious vice. God will haue all of vs or none of vs; though Sathan deſireth but any leaſt part, he wel know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:23753:47"/> that where he hath any thing at all, God will haue there nothing at all. He that breaketh one of the leaſt of theſe commandements ſhalbe the leaſt in the <note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> kingdome of God: <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, He that <note place="margin">Iames. 2.</note> breaketh one is guilty of all; and one vice is enough to ouerthrow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, though wee haue ſome vertues: one ſinne of couetouſneſs ouerthrew <hi>Iudas;</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a bribe got <hi>Gehezi</hi> the leproſie; <hi>Sampſon</hi> his luſt, loſt him his ſtrength and eies: <hi>Caines</hi> enuie made him ſo to ſinne as hee became accurſed: <hi>Iſmaels</hi> mocking caſt him forth: <hi>Eſaus</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe loſt him his birth-right: <hi>Ely</hi> his indulgency was his breaknecke: <hi>Michols</hi> deryding ſpirit made her bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren: and <hi>Ananias,</hi> for hypocriſie, was a ſpectacle of iudgement to others: <hi>Herod,</hi> albeit he doe many things, yet will haue his <hi>Herodias,</hi> his beloued ſinne ſtill, for enioying whereof wee are content to leaue other vices. I <note place="margin">Wee will leaue any ſin to keepe our beloued ſin.</note> will, ſaith the <hi>boone</hi> companion, doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing and let me bee but drunke: And I ſaith the carnall caitiffe, and let mee but ſatisfie my luſt, bee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, liue in dalliance and commit fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe:
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:23753:47"/> And I ſaith the couetous man, and let mee gaine goods and wealth: And I ſaith the proud man, and yield me honour; little knowing that ſuch a maiſter-ſinne is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his many attendants: It ruleth; but the other haue their power, to which the miſerable is alſo in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage vnwittingly: for we muſt know that no one vice wil be ſingled out from his fellowes: but if one get head, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue gone before as harbengers, and other waite and followe after as Aſſiſtants: one breedeth an other, and one nouriſheth an other conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie. Examples hereof, not onely in the wicked, who heape ſinne vpon ſinne, as <hi>Ioaſh</hi> murther to his Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, <hi>Iudas</hi> treaſon to his couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but euen in the falles of the faithfull children of GOD; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> his lying in the bed and gazing idlely abroad, bred his luſt, luſt adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and adultery murther.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſuch as ſuppoſe to walke with a partie coloured coate, betweene vertue and vice, or rather with ſome vertues, and ſome vices,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:23753:48"/> theſe men yet know not that vertue will dwell alone, as God; or vice alone; they are contraries, they neuer can accord in one; where vertues are careleſly negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, there no one vertue hath full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; and where any one ſinne bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſway, there viciouſneſſe is Lord &amp; maſter.</p>
               <p>Therefore let vs not doe this or that <note place="margin">The meere ciuill honeſt man is no commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> vertue, for ſo may we ſiniſterly; but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to doe all, and this is right. Many men go vnder a good name by ciuil ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, either thorow reſtrayned nature, or good education in commendable maners of ciuility, who are farre from ſanctification and the graces of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. They doe many actions of vertue, either of a cuſtome or by imitation, or reſpectiuely for this or that perſon, for this or that by-end; but not for vertue it ſelfe: neither doe they ſhew fruits of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, other then may preſerue common honeſty, their credit to liue amongſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to procure them praiſe; ſecret or leſſe publick they regard not: dueties of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, prayer, reading the ſcripture, ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying of the Sabaoth, inſtruction of their family, countenancing of the word
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:23753:48"/> preached, and ſuch like, they be ſo farre from, as they mock at men herein zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly affected: for vices which they ſhunne, they be ſuch onely, as be diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious, or odious amongſt men that haue but common honeſty: but to ſweare in ordinary communication, to be companions with men ſuperiour in place, how wicked ſoeuer, they make no conſcience of, neither of many other euils which by the rule of godlineſs are odious to God and ſuch as ſincerely ſeeke him. A ſanctified ſpirit doth not thus ſhuffle things together, neither ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a mixture of that which cannot be compounded: but they truly hate all vice, &amp; are affected to euery good thing; and become in their place, after the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace giuen them, doers of <hi>theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But leaſt naturall men ſhould carp &amp; <note place="margin">Preuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> ſay, Belike I wold haue men here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne, or elſe to be without grace; &amp; vnleſſe we do all things, we do nothing: I anſwere, It is not mine intendment to teach any ſuch thing; but that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould leaue ſin to the vtmoſt, &amp; not dally with any; that they ſhould doe vertuouſly &amp;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:23753:49"/> liue in purpoſe of heart, and will, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne. Legal obedience is beyond <note place="margin">what is le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> our power to performe, which is after the exactneſſe of the law, the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders holineſs, and mans perfection by creation, which we haue loſt, and is not here in our owne perſons recouerable, whatſoeuer the Phari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cal Papiſts ſay to the contrary: but I ſpeake of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <note place="margin">Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> and vertuous liuing Euangelically; which is an earneſt endeuour in loue &amp; thankfulnes to God for his mercies in Chriſt, in faith apprehending his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, in whom we be acceptable and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God, in truth and ſincerity of heart to doe whatſoeuer we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and is commended vnto vs: which will appeare by our ioy in well <note place="margin">Sig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>rity.</note> doing, by our prayers and holy deſires to doe well, by our feare to offend, &amp; by our ſorrow when we faile in our dueties; wherein ſtands the perfection of the beſt Chriſtian: wee can neither be equall to the lawe to fulfill it, nor go beyond to do more any way to merit. S. <hi>Paule</hi> in his Apoſtolical eſtate found imperfections: And <hi>Hezechias</hi> could ſpeak of vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but of no perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And thus much for the condition of the promiſe.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:23753:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye ſhall neuer fall.</hi> Ye ſhall neuer ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip or ſlide downe, ye ſhall not come to any <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> hurt: the word here vſed is drawne from the bodie to the minde, and is diuerſly taken in ſcripture; ſometime for ſinne; <hi>Prou.</hi> 24. 16. therefore is the word ſo tranſlated in the vulgar tranſlation: ſometime for deſtruction. 2. <hi>Sam. 3. 38. 1. Cor.</hi> 10. 8. ſometime to be downe on a ſodaine, ſo as a ſtanding and courſe is not kept; which is the common ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation thereof. All theſe three may here very fitly ſtand, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſinne, ye ſhall not be deſtroyed, ye ſhall not decline from your standing,</hi> to fall away from the ſtate of grace, whereunto ye are called. And therefore here I wil ſpeake of them all, as reaſons to ſpur vs on to a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life, which is the ſcope of the words.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Ye ſhall not ſinne.</hi> Vertuous men ſinne <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.</note> not. <hi>He that committeth ſinne is of the Diuel,</hi> and he that is borne of GOD ſinneth not: yet <hi>he that ſaith hee hath</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>no ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yer, and the truth is not in him.</hi> It is true neuertheleſſe, that he which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in Chriſt ſinneth not, ſuch do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 3</note> none iniquity; to wit, firſt in Gods acceptation, according to that ſaying,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:23753:50"/> 
                  <hi>He ſaw none iniquity in Iacob, nor tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">How god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are ſaid not to ſin. Num. 23. 21. Ier. 50. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>in Iſrael: their ſins ſhall not bee found</hi> ſaith <hi>Ieremie:</hi> and the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord will be mercifull vnto them; ſecondly in Chriſts ſatisfaction, in whom <hi>we are the righteouſneſs of God,</hi> and in him there is no condemnation. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">2 Cor 5. 21 Rom. 8. 1 Rom. 7.</note> in a godly mans will; for as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, good they would doe; and wherein they doe euill, they ſorrowe and would not doe; and herein the will ſtands for the deede. Laſtly in reſpect of time; for as the child of God ſinneth not wholly, ſo neither finally; for God hath put <hi>his feare into him, that hee ſhall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 32. 40. Pſ. 37. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>neuer depart from him;</hi> but <hi>if he fall, he ſhall not be caſt off, for the Lord putteth vnder his hand.</hi> Thus the vertuous ſinne not: and this grace ſhall be attained vnto by ſuch as doe theſe things, ſaith <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> Now this reaſon hath great force to perſwade vs to be vertuous: to bee free from ſinne is bleſſedneſſe, as <hi>Dauid</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 1. 2. This bleſſing can we not better know, then to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">What it is to ſin, and to liue therein.</note> what it is to ſinne, and to liue in it. It is the ſtate of corruption, ſeruice to the Diuell, contempt of Chriſts death,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:23753:50"/> the reſiſtance of grace, the racing out of Gods image, the bearing vpon vs the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uels likeneſſe: it is cauſe of calamities, the curſe in our calling, the eating can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker in the ſoule; the obiect of Gods wrath, and deaths ſting: it breaketh the vnion betweene God and vs, it maketh conſcience to accuſe, and the lawe to condemne, it maketh our life miſerable, death fearefull and the laſt day terrible: and to conclude, by it we loſe heauen, Angels attendance, ſaincts ſociety, and all celeſtiall comforts eternally; and we purchaſe hell; fiends attend vs, diuels accompany vs, the curſed crue of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſoules abide with vs, and we vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depriue our ſelues of all good, &amp; liue in woe and paines euerlaſtingly; This is to ſinne, this is to liue in ſinne; and not to ſinne is to be acceptable to God, in Chriſt righteous, our will plyable to his bidding, and our end comfortable as we to goodnes are conformeable.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Ye ſhall not be deſtroyed.</hi> The vertuous, as they ſinne not, ſo they periſh not. Godlineſs hath the promiſe of this life, and of the life to come: there is no cauſe of feare then; A great inducement to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:23753:51"/> liue vertuouſly, wee all naturally feare deſtruction, we deſire to preuent it no greater ioy then to be ſure of ſafe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> then let vs liue vprightly, embrace vertue, &amp; ſhun vice carefully: deſtruction remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for the vngodly, but peace and <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 16.</note> mercie to Syon and vpon the Iſraell of God. Let <hi>Pharao</hi> be drowned, the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites ſhall paſſe ouer ſafely: wicked Iſraelites may be deſtroyed, yet faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſua</hi> ſhall liue: <hi>Lotte</hi> ſhall eſcape, when Sodome ſhall flame with fire, and all the inhabitants ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And <hi>Noah</hi> with his ſhall be aliue in the Arke, when the whole world ſhal haue an end.</p>
               <p>Thus, vertuous men haue a <hi>Superſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas</hi> againſt Gods iuſtice, not of merit but in mercie: their ſoules be ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the blood of the Lamb, ſo that the Angell of wrath muſt paſſe ouer their perſons: they are aforehand mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Eze. 9.</note> in the forehead, for that they mourne &amp; cry for the abhominations which they ſee: theſe, the Angel muſt not ſo much as touch, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to ſmite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without pittie. O let vs therfore liue vertuouſly, and be doers of theſe things.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:23753:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye ſhall not leaue your ſtanding.</hi> You <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>e. Pſa. 15. 5</note> ſhall neuer, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, be moued, you ſhall not like dogs returne to the vomite againe, nor like ſwine to the <note place="margin">Ioh. 10. 28</note> myre: it is Chriſts promiſe, None ſhall pluck them out of his hands whom hee hath choſen: the more they exerciſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, the more they loue it, and grow more zealous in it. <hi>Dauid</hi> findeth the <note place="margin">Pſa. 19.</note> words of God ſweeter then honey, and the keeping of the commandements more precious then pearles: ſo is it with euerie one, that ſeeketh GOD in righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> This keeping of our ſtanding that we fall not away, is alſo a forcible reaſon to moue vs to exerciſe our ſelues in theſe vertues. What more comfort then euer to abide with God in the ſtate of grace? to call God father, Chriſt (the Iudge) our bleſſed ſauiour, the holy Ghoſt our comforter, glorious Angels our fellow ſeruant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, earth our right, and heauen our inheritance? And what more vncomfortable, then by falling away to bid adue to God, to grace &amp; to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? It is to cauſe the Lord to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre vs and to bid the Diuell take vs:
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:23753:52"/> It is to runne from vnder Gods prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and to ſeeke death and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: who therefore would not liue in doing vertuouſly, to keepe his ſtanding in the ſtate of grace that hee fall not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way?</p>
               <p>Doubt not of falling, if thou liue in Euangelicall obedience, &amp; in theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: thou haſt a perpetuall pledge of Gods loue, euen by thy godly life, his promiſes are annexed to ſuch a one; by well doing thou haſt aſſurance of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, and art in Gods ſeruice; and he that hath called thee, will mercifully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thee in the end. But many haue falne thou wilt ſay: true; from what they <note place="margin">Obiection anſwered.</note> ſeemed to bee, but not indeede from what they were: their gifts were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fauours, but not the ſpeciall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of election: they neuer attained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the aforenamed Euangelicall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; ſecretly they were hypocrites: none fall finally, but the good things they do, are done ſiniſterly, as appeareth in <hi>Iehu;</hi> and they nouriſh ſome ſinne which doth breake out at the length openly, as in <hi>Iudas</hi> is manifeſt. Search therefore thy ſelf how thou ſtandeſt: if vprightly with
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:23753:52"/> feare, loue, and in humility; feare not to fall finally. The elect fall for a time, as we ſee in <hi>Dauid:</hi> but they ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue not euer; this is the fall of a reprobate.</p>
               <p>If you demand how in falling we may know the difference betweene the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <note place="margin">A queſt.</note> and reprobate, it may appeare thus to a man; firſt by the truth of grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fall; by the remainder of grace in falling, with a kind of feare and with ſome ſtruggling vnwilling to yield, and yet through infirmity &amp; violence of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, forced to yield; for the godly truely conuerted cannot ſin after, with full conſent: Laſtly, after the fall to be checked in conſcience; and though for a time they do lie in ſin, yet then, not without the Lords externall chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to make them remember them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; when a faithful meſſenger co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, as <hi>Nathan,</hi> to ſay <hi>thou art the man, Dauid</hi> yieldeth and ſaith <hi>I haue ſinned;</hi> which the reprobate do not.</p>
               <p>If further through feare, thou that art in the ſtate of grace doſt obiect Sathans <note place="margin">Elect neede not to fear, they ſhall no way be ouercome.</note> powre; hee ſhall not preuaile; Chriſt hath ouercome him. <hi>Math.</hi> 4. And his triumph is thy victorie, ſo read it and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:23753:53"/> If thou dread the world, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Be of good comfort I haue ouercome the world.</hi> Iohn. 16. 33. If the fleſh which ouerthrew <hi>Salomon,</hi> &amp; conquered <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> hee that is in Chriſt hath mortified <note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> the deedes of the fleſh; and why was Chriſt pure, but to ſubdue thy corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? If yet thou ſay, But for all this, thou maiſt be ouercome by many temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; fall away in time of perſecution, remember that God wil not try thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue thy ſtrength. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13. And for other afflictions for Chriſt, in them thou ſhalt be more then a conqueror through him that loued vs. <hi>Rom</hi> 8. 37. And <hi>I am perſwaded that neither death nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to com, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſeparate vs from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> verſe. 38. 39. But many falſe teachers ſhall ariſe: true to deceiue certainly the reprobate, and to beguile the elect, if it were poſſible. <hi>Math</hi> 24. 24. But therefore it may bee inferred that it is an vnpoſſible thing; bee humble and meeke, for <hi>them that be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke will he guide in iudgement, and teach the humble his way.</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:23753:53"/> Pſal. 25. 9. Loue the truth for the truthes ſake, &amp; God wil not giue thee ouer to beleeue lies, as hee doth thoſe that haue not a loue of the truth. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 10. Oh, but I feare, my daily offences wil cauſe the Lord to caſt me off, to take his grace from me, &amp; ſo ſhall I fall finally. For this know, that the beſt ſinneth often<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; it is not ſinning but the lying in ſin that da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: If thou canſt confeſſe ſin &amp; forſake <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 13.</note> it, thou ſhalt haue mercie. <hi>Prou.</hi> 28. 13. though thou doſt fall, thou ſhalt not be caſt off, for the Lord putteth vnder his hand. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 24. To conclude, the Lord wil not forſake his people for his great names ſake, becauſe it hath pleaſed the Lord to make them his people. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 22. Thus ſaid <hi>Samuel</hi> to Iſrael to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort them, euen when they had greatly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God.</p>
               <p>Therefore let Sathan roare, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the earth, <hi>Iob</hi> is hedged about: let <note place="margin">A comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> the world lie in wickedneſſe, the elect ſhall ſee light to come out; the fleſh is ſtrong, but the ſpirit of God is ſtronger to caſt it out, to ſubdue and kil it: perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution ſhall not ouercome; the loue of Chriſt wil conſtraine vs to hold. Falſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:23753:54"/> teachers ſhall not miſlead vs ſo, but wee ſhall ſee &amp; returne, or preuent them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: &amp; though we ſin, yet this doth not condemne vs, for no Chriſtians; but that we are weake, and not wholly freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corruptions. Here is no perfection, here is vprightneſſe to bee had; hold this, beware of hypocriſie; ſtriue to perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that thou maiſt after attaine it in glory. So beloued ſhall no ſin raigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vs, grace ſhall grow in vs, peace ſhal be vpon vs, faith ſhal ſet comfort before vs, this wretched worlde ſhall not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch vs, pleaſures ſhall not deceiue vs, nor any thing cauſe vs to miſcarie, but that wee ſhall run on &amp; run out our race with ioy, vntill the full end of our daies. Which, the Father of mercy, &amp; the God of all comforts graunt vnto vs, for his ſonnes ſake, Chriſt Ieſus. To whom with the Father, and the holy Spirit, be euerlaſting praiſe and glory, for this his grace, and all other his mercies, now and henceforth for euermore.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23753:54"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
